<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hanslick Online - Hanslick’s Historical Relevance</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName resp="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1226158307">Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bäckerstraße 13</addrLine>
               <addrLine>1010 Vienna</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2023">2025</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body xml:lang="en-US">
         <div type="main">
            <div type="sub">
               <head>Hanslick’s Historical Relevance</head>
               <byline>Alexander Wilfing, 2023</byline>
               <div type="inline">
                  <p>Eduard Hanslick is known to many people today primarily as a music critic, as a
                     friend of Brahms and an enemy of Wagner, on the whole as “il Bismarck della
                     critica musicale,” as whom—as Hanslick himself reports in his autobiography
                           <emph><ref
                           target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11557245?q=%28eduard+hanslick+Musikalisches+Skizzenbuch%29&amp;page=300,301"
                           >Aus meinem Leben</ref></emph> (From my Life)—he was dubbed by none other
                     than Guiseppe Verdi, whose <emph>Falstaff</emph> would later be the subject of
                     Hanslick’s final review (<ref
                        target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=nfp&amp;datum=19040407&amp;seite=1&amp;zoom=33"
                           ><emph>Neue Freie Presse</emph>, April 7, 1904</ref>). To the opera and
                     concert audience of today, Hanslick is a household name as a constant feature
                     of program guides, more often than not assuming the role of the reactionary who
                     had been overtaken by historical developments. Hanslick’s opposition to
                     Wagner’s late operas, Liszt’s symphonic poems, and the subsequent offshoots of
                     the so-called New German School in particular, as well as his lack of
                     understanding of composers like Richard Strauss and Gustav Mahler—whom he
                     candidly admired as a conductor—have nourished this reputation. Thus, it is not
                     at all surprising that he is also prominently represented in Nicholas
                     Slonimsky’s <emph>Lexicon of Musical Invective: Critical Assaults on Composers
                        since Beethoven’s Time</emph> (1953, reprinted 2000) and is repeatedly
                     identified with the stage figure of Beckmesser, as illustrated succinctly by
                     Norbert Tschulik’s collection <emph>Also sprach Beckmesser: Aus den Schriften
                        von Eduard Hanslick</emph> (Thus spoke Beckmesser: From the writings of
                     Eduard Hanslick; 1965). The fact that Hanslick’s writings continue to be cited
                     all the same is due not only to their content but for the most part to the
                     critic’s refined writing style and his (often all too) sharp tongue, which
                     makes reading his texts seem worthwhile even after this many a year. There are
                     refreshingly sardonic passages, such as his praise for <emph>Die Meistersinger
                        von Nürnberg</emph>, which as a “memorable artistic experience,” and despite
                     its “interesting musical exceptions or symptoms of illness,” seems to Hanslick
                     “more significant and lastingly stimulating than a dozen garden-variety operas
                     by those numerous healthy composers to whom one pays half too much honor by
                     calling them half-talents” (<ref
                        target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=nfp&amp;datum=18680626&amp;seite=2&amp;zoom=33"
                           ><emph>Neue Freie Presse</emph>, June 26, 1868</ref>), alongside
                     questionable remarks such as the (in)famous reflection on the occasion of
                     Tchaikovsky’s violin concerto “whether there could not also be pieces of music
                     that one hears stink” (<ref
                        target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=nfp&amp;datum=18811224&amp;seite=1&amp;zoom=33"
                           ><emph>Neue Freie Presse</emph>, December 24, 1881</ref>).</p>
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="images/csm_Eduard_Hanslick_344df3fc95.jpg"/>
                        <head>Eduard Hanslick, photograph by Ludwig Grillich (1892); by courtesy of <ref target="https://onb.digital/result/BAG_19676858">Österreichische Nationalbibliothek</ref></head>
                        <!--<figDesc>...</figDesc>-->
                     </figure>
               </div>
               <div type="inline">
                  <figure>
                     <graphic url="images/csm_Dwight_s_Journal_of_Music_a32ce300f3.jpg"/>
                     <head>Review of <emph>Die Meistersinger von Nürnberg</emph>, <ref
                           target="https://books.google.at/books?id=jxVOAAAAYAAJ&amp;hl=de&amp;pg=PA281#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                              ><emph>Dwight’s Journal of Music</emph>, August 1, 1868</ref></head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Whatever one may think of these statements, Hanslick’s prominence as presumably
                     the most important music critic of his era is likely due to such provocative
                     positions as well as his profile as an (or <emph>the</emph>) opponent of the
                     New German School. His reputation as a consistently conservative music critic,
                     a “stodgy, pedantic spokesperson for ‘conservative’ musical causes,” as Dana
                        Gooley—<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1525/jm.2011.28.3.289">“Hanslick and
                        the Institution of Criticism,” <emph>Journal of Musicology</emph> 28, no. 3
                        (2011), 289</ref>—encapsulates a widespread stereotype, is, however, clearly
                     exaggerated: Although Hanslick certainly regarded the motivic-thematic work of
                     Brahms and Beethoven as the ideal of music and considered Wagner’s “infinite
                     melody”—which he in later editions labeled as “formlessness elevated to a
                     principle” and a “sung and fiddled opium high” (<ref
                        target="diff_V2.6.html?lang=de">editions 4–10, V2.6</ref>; <emph>Eduard
                        Hanslick’s ‘On the Musically Beautiful’: A New Translation</emph>, trans. by
                     Lee Rothfarb and Christoph Landerer, Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018,
                     lxxxi)—an aberration, he could also warm to more modern composers like Antonin
                     Dvořák, Edvard Grieg, and Bedřich Smetana. His reach was accordingly not
                     limited to Vienna, Austria, and the German-speaking world, but already attained
                     international proportions during his own lifetime. The <emph><ref
                           target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwight%27s_Journal_of_Music"
                           >Journal of Music</ref></emph>, edited by the Boston critic John Sullivan
                     Dwight (1813–1893), which appeared between 1852 and 1881 with financial support
                     from the Harvard Musical Association, is particularly representative. Dwight,
                     who shared and occasionally surpassed Hanslick’s classicist conviction,
                     translated a range of Hanslick’s reviews into English, so that between 1866 and
                     1881 more than three dozen of his essays reached a Boston audience. Hanslick’s
                     reputation was also nourished by his participation in international musical
                     events and in-depth travel reports from, among other places, Bayreuth, London,
                     and Paris. These extensive musico-critical activities ultimately resulted in
                     Hanslick sitting on renowned music juries—this way, for example, he procured
                     state grants for Dvořák between 1874 and 1877— and repeatedly attending
                     international exhibitions as a correspondent and later as an Austrian delegate,
                     for example at the World’s Fairs in London (1862), Paris (1867), and Vienna
                     (1873).</p>
               </div>
               <div type="inline">
                  <p>While Hanslick’s prominence among the musical public is closely linked to his
                     critiques and the figure of Wagner, his continued importance in philosophy and
                     musicology depends on other aspects of his work: In 1856, Hanslick was
                     appointed lecturer for the “History and Aesthetics of Musical Art,” the
                     earliest such position not only in Vienna but rather in the entire
                     German-speaking world. Although music history had been taught at universities
                     since the eighteenth century, until then the activity was for the most part
                     tantamount to the post of a practical music director. The theoretically
                     oriented lectureship of Hanslick, who was appointed associate professor in 1861
                     and full professor in 1870, was a novelty that is now considered the first
                     professorship of musicology, which has been generally known under that name
                     only since the founding of the <emph><ref
                           target="https://de.wikisource.org/wiki/Vierteljahrsschrift_f%C3%BCr_Musikwissenschaft"
                           >Vierteljahrsschrift für Musikwissenschaft</ref></emph> (Musicology
                     Quarterly; 1885). (On the history of the discipline in Vienna, see <ref
                        target="https://musikwissenschaft.univie.ac.at/ueber-uns/institutsgeschichte/chronik/"
                        >this link</ref>.) In 1869, Hanslick published volume 1 of <emph><ref
                           target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb10598665?page=4,5"
                           >Geschichte des Concertwesens in Wien</ref></emph> (History of the Vienna
                     concert scene), which could be considered a pioneering achievement in the
                     sociology of music, as his only historical work in a narrow sense. Later books
                     are composed primarily of collected reviews, reports, and essays that Hanslick
                     wanted to be understood as a living history of music in Vienna and as
                     “aesthetic statistics of opera” (<ref
                        target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11081548?page=8,9"
                           ><emph>Die Moderne Oper</emph>, 1:vi</ref>). In <emph>Music, Criticism,
                        and the Challenge of History</emph> (Oxford University Press 2008, chap. 2),
                     Kevin Karnes frames this approach with reference to Dilthey, Droysen, and
                     Burckhardt as an early attempt at particularistic historiography, which,
                     however, did not prevail historically against philological musicology as
                     developed by Friedrich Chrysander, Otto Jahn, and Philipp Spitta, among others.
                     Even if Hanslick’s relevance for the genesis of academic musicology is for the
                     most part underestimated, his importance as a founder of the discipline
                     nevertheless clearly falls short of that of his successor Guido Adler, who
                     established the Department of Musicology in Vienna in 1901 and shaped the
                     methodology of the discipline for many years with his 1885 essay “<ref
                        target="https://www.digizeitschriften.org/id/479007071_0001%7Clog1?tify=%7B%22pages%22%3A"
                        >Umfang, Methode und Ziel der Musikwissenschaft</ref>” (translated as “<ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.2307/768355">Scope, Method, and Aim of
                        Musicology</ref>”). </p>
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="images/csm_Alte_Universitaet_Wien_39f321d9a4.jpg"/>
                        <head>The former venue of the University of Vienna, ca. 1850; by courtesy of <ref target="https://onb.digital/result/BAG_12352553">Österreichische Nationalbibliothek</ref></head>
                     </figure>
               </div>
               <div type="inline">
                  <figure>
                     <graphic url="images/csm_VMS_1854_43ca3476ef.jpg"/>
                     <head>Cover of Eduard Hanslick’s treatise <ref
                           target="https://archive.org/details/VomMusikalischSchnen1tea1854/mode/2up"
                              ><emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>, 1st edition, 1854</ref></head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>In addition to Hanslick’s roles as a music critic and professor of the “History
                     and Aesthetics of Musical Art,” his name remains closely associated with a book
                     he wrote at the age of only 29: <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen: Ein Beitrag zur
                        Revision der Aesthetik der Tonkunst</emph> or <emph>On the Musically
                        Beautiful: A Contribution to the Revision of the Aesthetics of Music</emph>.
                     This book, which went through ten revised editions during Hanslick’s lifetime
                     (see the index of Eduard Hanslick’s writings below), can be characterized
                     without exaggeration as the most impactful musico-aesthetic treatise of the
                     nineteenth century, whose central assertions continue to inform debates in
                     aesthetics. <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> (<emph>VMS</emph> for short)
                     develops a perspective specifically derived from the intrinsic properties of
                     musical material, whose focus on the object, critical stance against
                     metaphysical speculation, and up-to-date definition of the problem of music and
                     emotion—reminiscent of the twentieth-century cognitivist concept of
                     emotion—remain relevant to contemporary discourse. Historically speaking,
                     particular importance was attributed to Hanslick’s much-cited rejection of the
                     “rotten aesthetics of feeling”—a phrase found only in the preface to the first
                     edition (<ref target="diff_V1.4.html?lang=en">V1.4</ref>)—which, like the
                     analogy between the content of music and the moving arabesque, as well as the
                     notorious catchphrase “the content of music is <emph>sonically moved
                        forms</emph>” (<ref target="diff_3.6.html?lang=de">editions 4–10, 3.6</ref>;
                     Rothfarb and Landerer, <emph>On the Musically Beautiful</emph>, 41), shape
                     Hanslick's reception to the present day. Here, too, the radiance of Hanslick’s
                     treatise, which its translator Geoffrey Payzant, for example, deemed the
                     “founding document of musical aesthetics as we know it” (<emph>Hanslick on the
                        Musically Beautiful: Sixteen Lectures on the Musical Aesthetics of Eduard
                        Hanslick</emph>, Christchurch: Cybereditions 2002, 17), rapidly outgrew
                     German-language discourse. The reputation of <emph>VMS</emph> as a pamphlet
                     directed primarily against Richard Wagner—a reputation undoubtably encouraged
                     in the prefaces of later editions (as was already evident from Hanslick’s
                     polemic against Wagner’s “infinite melody”) and certainly not detrimental to
                     the popularity of this book—clearly falls short, however, and also does not do
                     full justice to Hanslick’s impact.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="inline">
                  <p>The reception of Hanslick’s writings markedly goes beyond his own epoch and,
                     with regard to music philosophy and musicology, encompasses such central
                     figures as Guido Adler, Friedrich Nietzsche, Heinrich Schenker, and Ludwig
                     Wittgenstein. Generally speaking, the impact of <emph>VMS</emph>, which
                     stretches from the beginnings of academic music research to numerous composers
                     (Pfitzner, Schoenberg, Stravinsky) and established philosophers like Theodor W.
                     Adorno, Karl Popper, and Roman Ingarden, has hardly been researched
                     systematically up to this point. Corresponding research literature is mostly
                     limited to passing references regarding certain analogies between Hanslick and
                     later authors, which often remain vague and do not seriously examine
                     reception-historical correlations. There are notable parallels between
                     Hanslick’s treatise and the late philosophy of Wittgenstein, for example, who
                     determined the meaning of a piece of music to be specifically musical and
                     decidedly rejected the idea that music could be successfully verbalized. While
                     these contexts have hardly been explored, Nietzsche’s relationship with
                     Hanslick, from his <emph><ref
                           target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb10999253?page=4,5"
                           >Geburt der Tragödie aus dem Geiste der Musik</ref></emph> (The Birth of
                     Tragedy Out of the Spirit of Music, 1872) to his late works—<emph>Der Fall
                        Wagner </emph> (The Case of Wagner, 1888) and <emph>Nietzsche contra
                        Wagner</emph> (1889), which take a reserved approach to Wagner—has often
                     been the subject of research. Furthermore, VMS fell on particularly fertile
                     ground with modern analytical philosophy of music and its focus on the
                     relationship between emotion and music as well as its distinctly objective
                     orientation. Although Hanslick already played a major role in the context of
                     Susanne K. Langer’s <emph>Philosophy in a New Key</emph> (1942),
                        <emph>VMS</emph> moved to the center of the debate around the 1980s. This
                     development depends primarily on the relevance of the cognitivist concept of
                     emotion in analytical discourse on music, which is laid out explicitly in
                        <emph>VMS</emph> and attracted the attention of contemporary philosophers
                     such as Malcolm Budd, Peter Kivy, and Stephen Davies. (A detailed analysis of
                     Hanslick’s reception in the English-speaking world can be found under <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctvktrwbs">this link</ref>). Although no
                     modern aesthetic theorist is in complete agreement with Hanslick’s position,
                     his framing of issues like the relation of music to affect states (feelings,
                     emotions, moods, etc.), the autonomy of the “work of art,” or the aesthetic
                     significance of musical facture, among others, has had lasting impact and
                     continues to influence related debates to this day.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <graphic url="images/csm_Collage_Rezeption_26b56785ee.jpg"/>
                     <head>Collage of images of <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guido_Adler_(Musikwissenschaftler)#/media/Datei:GuidoAdler.png">Adler</ref>, <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedrich_Nietzsche#/media/Datei:Nietzsche187a.jpg">Nietzsche</ref>, <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinrich_Schenker#/media/Datei:Hermann_Clemens_Kosel_Heinrich_Schenker_1912.jpg">Schenker</ref>, and <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludwig_Wittgenstein#/media/Datei:Ludwig_Wittgenstein_(cropped).jpg">Wittgenstein</ref> (Wikipedia Creative Commons)</head>
                  </figure>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="sub">
               <head>Eduard Hanslick’s Writings</head>
               <div type="block">
                  <list type="bibl">
                     <item>“Ueber den subjektiven Eindruck der Musik und seine Stellung in der
                        Aesthetik,” <emph>Oesterreichische Blätter für Literatur und Kunst</emph>
                        <ref target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=wrz&amp;datum=18530725&amp;seite=5&amp;zoom=33">30 (1853): 177–178;</ref>
                        <ref target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=wrz&amp;datum=18530801&amp;seite=7&amp;zoom=33">31 (1853): 181–182</ref>; <ref target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=wrz&amp;datum=18530815&amp;seite=3&amp;zoom=33">33 (1853): 193–195</ref>.</item>
                     <item><ref target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=wrz&amp;datum=18540313&amp;seite=6&amp;zoom=33">“Die Tonkunst in ihren Beziehungen zur
                           Natur,”</ref> <emph>Oesterreichische Blätter für Literatur und
                           Kunst</emph> 11 (1854): 78–80.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://hanslick.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/t__01_VMS_1854_TEI_AW_26-01-21-TEI-P5.html">Vom Musikalisch-Schönen: Ein Beitrag zur Revision der Aesthetik der
                              Tonkunst</ref></emph>, Leipzig: Rudolph Weigel, 1854. Further
                        editions: <list>
                           <item><ref target="https://hanslick.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/t__02_VMS_1858_TEI_AW_26-01-21-TEI-P5.html">2nd edition</ref>, Leipzig: Rudolph Weigel, 1858.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://hanslick.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/t__03_VMS_1865_TEI_AW_26-01-21-TEI-P5.html">3rd edition</ref>, Leipzig: Rudolph Weigel, 1865.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://hanslick.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/t__04_VMS_1874_TEI_AW_26-01-21-TEI-P5.html">4th edition</ref>, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1874.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://hanslick.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/t__05_VMS_1876_TEI_AW_26-01-21-TEI-P5.html">5th edition</ref>, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1876.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://hanslick.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/t__06_VMS_1881_TEI_AW_26-01-21-TEI-P5.html">6th edition</ref>, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1881.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://hanslick.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/t__07_VMS_1885_TEI_AW_26-01-21-TEI-P5.html">7th edition</ref>, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1885.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://hanslick.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/t__08_VMS_1891_TEI_AW_26-01-21-TEI-P5.html">8th edition</ref>, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1891.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://hanslick.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/t__09_VMS_1896_TEI_AW_26-01-21-TEI-P5.html">9th edition</ref>, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1896.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://hanslick.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/t__10_VMS_1902_TEI_AW_26-01-21-TEI-P5.html">10th edition</ref>, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1902.</item>
                        </list></item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb10598665?page=4,5">Geschichte des Concertwesens in Wien</ref></emph>, Vienna: Wilhelm
                        Braumüller, 1869.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11727302?page=,1">Geschichte des Concertwesens in Wien</ref></emph>, vol. 2, <emph>Aus
                           dem Concertsaal: Kritiken und Schilderungen aus den letzten 20 Jahren des
                           Wiener Musiklebens nebst einem Anhang, Musikalische Reisebriefe aus
                           England, Frankreich und der Schweiz</emph>, Vienna: Wilhelm Braumüller,
                        1870.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11081548?page=4,5">Die moderne Oper: Kritiken und Studien</ref></emph>, Berlin: A.
                        Hofmann, 1875.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11727297?page=8,9">Musikalische Stationen: Neue Folge der “Modernen Oper,”</ref></emph>
                        Berlin: A. Hofmann, 1880.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11556958?page=8,9">Aus dem Opernleben der Gegenwart: Der “Modernen Oper” III. Theil;
                              Neue Kritiken und Studien</ref></emph>, Berlin: A. Hofmann,
                        1884.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11556962?page=8,9">Suite: Aufsätze über Musik und Musiker</ref></emph>, Vienna: Franz
                        Prochaska, 1884.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11556956?page=8,9">Concerte, Componisten und Virtuosen der letzten fünfzehn Jahre, 1870–1885: Kritiken</ref></emph>, Berlin: Allgemeiner Verein für deutsche Literatur, 1886.</item>
                     <item><ref target="https://austria-forum.org/web-books/kpwde01de1886onb/00000138">“Die Musik in Wien,”</ref> in <emph>Die österreichisch-ungarische
                           Monarchie in Wort und Bild</emph>, vol. 1, <emph>Wien und
                           Niederösterreich</emph>, ed. by crown prince archduke Rudolf, Vienna:
                        Druck und Verlag der k. u. k. Hof- und Staatsdruckerei, 1886,
                        123–138.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://archive.org/details/musikalischessk00hansgoog/page/n8/mode/2up">Musikalisches Skizzenbuch: Der “Modernen Oper” IV. Theil; Neue
                              Kritiken und Schilderungen</ref></emph>, Berlin: Allgemeiner Verein
                        für deutsche Litteratur, 1888.</item>
                     <item><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11472059?q=%28eduard+hanslick+Wien+1848%E2%80%931888%29&amp;page=312,313">“Musik,”</ref> in <emph>Wien 1848–1888: Denkschrift zum 2. December
                           1888</emph>, ed. by the Vienna City Council, Vienna: Carl Konegen, 1888,
                        2:301–342.</item>
                     <item><ref target="https://austria-forum.org/web-books/kpwde04de1888onb/00000265">“Volksmusik, Dialect und Dialectpoesie,”</ref> in <emph>Die
                           österreichisch-ungarische Monarchie in Wort und Bild</emph>, vol. 2,
                           <emph>Niederösterreich</emph>, ed. by crown prince archduke Rudolf,
                        Vienna: Druck und Verlag der k. u. k. Hof- und Staatsdruckerei, 1888,
                        251–262 (in collaboration with Richard von Muth).</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11556960?page=4,5">Musikalisches und Litterarisches: Der “Modernen Oper” V. Theil;
                              Kritiken und Schilderungen</ref></emph>, Berlin: Allgemeiner Verein
                        für deutsche Litteratur, 1889.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11556961?page=10,11">Aus dem Tagebuche eines Musikers: Der “Modernen Oper” VI. Theil;
                              Kritiken und Schilderungen</ref></emph>, Berlin: Allgemeiner Verein
                        für deutsche Litteratur, 1892.</item>
                     <item><emph>Aus meinem Leben</emph>, Berlin: Allgemeiner Verein für deutsche
                        Litteratur, 1894, <ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11573682?page=6,7">vol. 1</ref> and <ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11557245?page=12,13">vol. 2</ref>.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_Yh1NAAAAMAAJ/page/n7/mode/2up">Fünf Jahre Musik, 1891–1895: Der “Modernen Oper” VII. Theil;
                              Kritiken</ref></emph>, Berlin: Allgemeiner Verein für deutsche
                        Litteratur, 1896.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://archive.org/details/amendedesjahrhun08hans/page/n3/mode/2up">Am Ende des Jahrhunderts, 1895–1899: Der “Modernen Oper” VIII. Teil;
                              Musikalische Kritiken und Schilderungen</ref></emph>, Berlin:
                        Allgemeiner Verein für deutsche Litteratur, 1899.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://archive.org/details/ausneuerundneue00hansgoog/page/n5/mode/2up">Aus neuer und neuerster Zeit: Der “Modernen Oper” IX. Teil;
                              Musikalische Kritiken und Schilderungen</ref></emph>, Berlin:
                        Allgemeiner Verein für deutsche Litteratur, 1900.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <div type="block">
                     <head>Translations of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph></head>
                        <div type="block"><list type="bibl">
                        <item>Albanian: <emph>Për të bukurën muzikore</emph>, transl. by Bekim
                           Ramadani, Tetovo: Universiteti Shtetëror i Tetovës, Fakulteti i muzikës,
                           2014.</item>
                        <item>Bengali: <emph>Saṃgīte sundara</emph>, transl. by [unknown],
                           Calcutta: Jijnāsā, 1969.</item>
                        <item>Bulgarian: <emph>Za muzikalno krasivoto</emph>, transl. by Maria
                           Kaitazov, Sofia: LIK, 1998.</item>
                        <item>Catalan: <emph>Sobre la bellesa musical</emph>, transl. by Ariadna
                           Soler i Subils and Oriol Ponsatí-Murlà, Girona: Accent, 2010.</item>
                        <item>Chinese: <emph>Lun yin le de mei</emph>, transl. by Yang Ye Zhi,
                           Peking: Ren min yin le chu ban she, 1980.</item>
                        <item>Czech: <emph>O hudebním krásnu</emph>, transl. by Jaroslav
                           Střítecký, Prague: Editio Supraphon, 1973.</item>
                        <item>Dutch: <emph>Over het begrip van schoon in de muziek</emph>, transl.
                           by Daniel Kiehl, Den Haag: D. N. F. Kiehl, 1892.</item>
                        <item>English: <emph>The Beautiful in Music</emph>, transl. by Gustav Cohen,
                           London: Novello and Company, 1891.</item>
                        <item>English: <emph>On the Musically Beautiful</emph>, transl. by Geoffrey
                           Payzant, Indianapolis: Hackett Publishing, 1986.</item>
                        <item>English: <emph>Eduard Hanslick’s ‘On the Musically Beautiful’</emph>,
                           transl. by Lee Rothfarb and Christoph Landerer, Oxford: Oxford University
                           Press, 2018.</item>
                        <item>Finnish: <emph>Musiikille ominaisesta kauneudesta</emph>, transl. by
                           Ilkka Oramo, Tampere: Niin &amp; Näin, 2014.</item>
                        <item>French: <emph>Du beau dans la musique</emph>, transl. by Charles
                           Bannelier, Paris: Brandus, 1877.</item>
                        <item>French: <emph>Du beau dans la musique</emph>, transl. by Jean-Jacques
                           Nattiez, Paris: Bourgois, 1986.</item>
                        <item>French: <emph>Du beau musical</emph>, transl. by Alexandre Lissner,
                           Paris: Hermann, 2012.</item>
                        <item>Hungarian: <emph>A zenei szép</emph>, transl. by Csobó Péter
                           György, Budapest: Typotex, 2007.</item>
                        <item>Italian: <emph>Del bello nella musica</emph>, transl. by Luigi Torchi,
                           Milan: Ricordi, 1883.</item>
                        <item>Italian: <hi rend="italic">Il bello musicale</hi>, transl. by
                           Mariangela Dona, Milan: Minuziano, 1945.</item>
                        <item>Italian: <hi rend="italic">Il bello musicale</hi>, transl. by Leonardo
                           Distaso, Palermo: Aesthetica, 2001.</item>
                        <item>Japanese: <emph>Hansurikku no ongaku biron</emph>, transl. by Hirosada
                           Tamura, Tokyo: Iwanami Shoten, 1924.</item>
                        <item>Japanese: <emph>Ongaku biron</emph>, transl. by Mamoru Watanabe,
                           Tokyo: Iwanami Shoten, 1960.</item>
                        <item>Macedonian: <emph>Za muzički ubavoto</emph>, transl. by Sašo
                           Milenkoski, Skopje: Kulturno-Informativen Centar, 2009.</item>
                           <item>Norwegian: <emph>Om Det Skjønne i Musikken</emph>, transl. by Karl Bjørset,
                              Bergen: Huuns Forlag, 1885.</item>
                        <item>Polish: <emph>O pięknie w muzyce</emph>, transl. by Stanisław
                           Niewiadomski, Warsaw: Arct, 1903.</item>
                        <item>Polish: <emph>O pie̢knie muzycznym</emph>, transl. by Joanna Giel,
                           Wrocław: Wydawnictwo Uniwersytetu Wrocławskiego, 2017.</item>
                        <item>Portuguese: <emph>Do belo musical</emph>, transl. by Simone Neto,
                           Campinas: Editora da Unicamp, 1992. </item>
                        <item>Portuguese: <emph>Do belo musical</emph>, transl. by Artur Morão,
                           Covilhã: Universidade da Beira Interior, 2011.</item>
                        <item>Russian: <emph>O muzykalʹno-prekrasnom</emph>, transl. by G. A.
                           Laroche, Moscow: Jurgensona, 1895.</item>
                        <item>Schwedish: <emph>Om det sköna i musiken</emph>, transl. by Britta
                           Collinder, Uppsala: Almqvist &amp; Wiksells, 1955.</item>
                        <item>Serbian: <emph>O muzički lijepom</emph>, transl. by Ivan Foht,
                           Belgrade: Beogradski Izdavačko-Grafički Zavod, 1977.</item>
                        <item>Spanish: <emph>De la belleza en la música</emph>, transl. by Elisa de
                           Luxán de García Dana, Madrid: Casa Editorial de Medina, 1865.</item>
                        <item>Spanish: <emph>De lo bello en la música</emph>, transl. by Alfredo
                           Cahn, Buenos Aires: Ricordi, 1947.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="block">
                  <head>Other English-Language Translations of Hanslick’s Writings</head>
                  <div type="block">
                     <list type="bibl">
                        <item><emph>Vienna’s Golden Years of Music, 1850–1900</emph>, trans. by Henry Pleasants, New York: Simon and Schuster, 1950.</item>
                        <item><emph>Eduard Hanslick: Music Criticisms 1846–1899</emph>, trans. by Henry Pleasants, London: Penguin Books, 1963.</item>
                        <item><emph>Hanslickʼs Music Criticisms</emph>, trans. by Henry Pleasants, New York: Dover Publications, 1988.</item>
                        <item>“Eduard Hanslick: Brahms’s Newest Instrumental Compositions (1889),” trans. by Susan Gillespie, in <emph>Brahms and His World</emph>, ed. by Walter Frisch, Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1990, 145–150.</item>
                        <item>“Eduard Hanslick: Memories and Letters,” trans. by Susan Gillespie, in <emph>Brahms and His World</emph>, ed. by Walter Frisch, Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1990, 163–184.</item>
                        <item>“Hanslick contra Wagner: ‘The Ring Cycle Comes to Vienna’ and ‘Parsifal Literature,’” trans. by Thomas Grey, in <emph>Richard Wagner and His World</emph>, ed. by Thomas Grey, Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2009, 409–425.</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">From My Life: The Autobiography of Eduard
                              Hanslick</hi>, ed. by Tom Moore, Lanham: Rowman &amp; Littlefield
                           2023.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </div> 
            </div>
         </div>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
