<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hanslick Online - Historische Bedeutung</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName resp="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1226158307">Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bäckerstraße 13</addrLine>
               <addrLine>1010 Vienna</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2023">2023</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body xml:lang="en-US">
         <div type="main">
            <div type="sub">
               <head>Hanslick’s Historical Relevance</head>
               <byline>Alexander Wilfing, 2023</byline>
               <div type="inline">
                  <p>Eduard Hanslick is known to many people today primarily as a music critic, as a
                     friend of Brahms and an enemy of Wagner, by and large as “il Bismarck della
                     critica musicale,” as whom—as Hanslick himself reports in his autobiography
                           <emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11557245?q=%28eduard+hanslick+Musikalisches+Skizzenbuch%29&amp;page=300,301">Aus meinem Leben</ref></emph> (From my Life)—he was dubbed
                     by none other than Guiseppe Verdi, whose <emph>Falstaff</emph> would later
                     become the subject of Hanslick’s final review (<ref target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=nfp&amp;datum=19040407&amp;seite=1&amp;zoom=33"><emph>Neue Freie Presse</emph>, April 7, 1904</ref>). To the opera and
                     concert audience of today, he is a household name as a constant feature of
                     program guides, with Hanslick more often than not assuming the role of the
                     reactionary who had been overtaken by historical developments. Hanslick’s
                     opposition to Wagner’s late operas, Listzt’s symphonic poems, and the
                     subsequent offshoots of the so-called New German School in particular, as well
                     as his lack of understanding of composers like Richard Strauss and Gustav
                     Mahler—who he candidly admired as a conductor—have nourished this reputation.
                     Thus, it is not at all surprising that he is also prominently represented in
                     Nicholas Slonimsky’s <emph>Lexicon of Musical Invective: Critical Assaults on
                        Composers Since Beethoven’s Time</emph> (1953, reprinted 2000) and is
                     repeatedly identified with the stage figure of Beckmesser, as Norbert
                     Tschulik’s collection <emph>Also sprach Beckmesser: Aus den Schriften von
                        Eduard Hanslick</emph> (Thus Spoke Beckmesser: From the Writings of Eduard
                     Hanslick; 1965) illustrates succinctly. The fact that Hanslick’s writings
                     continue to be cited all the same is due not only to their content but for the
                     most part to the critic’s refined writing style and his (often all too) sharp
                     tongue, which makes reading his texts seem worthwhile even after this many a
                     year. There are refreshingly sardonic passages, such as his praise for
                        <emph>Die Meistersinger von Nürnberg</emph>, which as a “memorable artistic
                     experience” and despite its “interesting musical exceptions or symptoms of
                     illness” seem to Hanslick “more significant and lastingly stimulating than a
                     dozen garden-variety operas by those numerous healthy composers to whom one
                     pays too much honor by half by calling them half-talents” (<ref target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=nfp&amp;datum=18680626&amp;seite=2&amp;zoom=33"><emph>Neue Freie Presse</emph>, June 26, 1868</ref>), alongside
                     questionable remarks such as the (in)famous reflection on the occasion of
                     Tchaikovsky’s violin concerto “whether there could not also be pieces of music
                     that one hears stink” (<ref target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=nfp&amp;datum=18811224&amp;seite=1&amp;zoom=33"><emph>Neue Freie Presse</emph>, December 24, 1881</ref>).</p>
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="images/csm_Eduard_Hanslick_344df3fc95.jpg"/>
                        <head>Eduard Hanslick, photograph by Ludwig Grillich (1892); by courtesy of <ref target="https://onb.digital/result/BAG_19676858">Österreichische Nationalbibliothek</ref></head>
                        <!--<figDesc>...</figDesc>-->
                     </figure>
               </div>
               <div type="inline">
                  <figure>
                     <graphic url="images/csm_Dwight_s_Journal_of_Music_a32ce300f3.jpg"/>
                     <head>Hanslick’s review of <emph>Die Meistersinger von Nürnberg</emph>, <ref target="https://books.google.at/books?id=jxVOAAAAYAAJ&amp;hl=de&amp;pg=PA281#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"><emph>Dwight’s Journal of Music</emph>, August 1, 1868</ref></head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Whatever one may think of these statements, Hanslick’s prominence as presumably
                     the most important music critic of his era is likely due to such provocative
                     positions as well as his profile as an (or <emph>the</emph>) opponent of the
                     New German School. His reputation as a consistently conservative music critic,
                     a “stodgy, pedantic spokesperson for ‘conservative’ musical causes,” as Dana
                     Gooley—<ref target="https://doi.org/10.1525/jm.2011.28.3.289">“Hanslick and the Institution of Criticism,” <emph>Journal of
                        Musicology</emph> 28, no. 3 (2011), 289</ref>—encapsulates a widespread
                     stereotype, is, however, clearly exaggerated: Although Hanslick certainly
                     regarded the motivic-thematic work of Brahms and Beethoven as the ideal of
                     music and considered Wagner’s “infinite melody”—which he in later editions
                     labelled as “formlessness elevated to a principle” and a “sung and fiddled
                     opium high” (<emph>Eduard Hanslick’s ‘On the Musically Beautiful’: A New
                        Translation</emph>, trans. by Lee Rothfarb and Christoph Landerer, Oxford:
                     Oxford University Press, 2018, lxxxi)—an aberration, he could also warm to more
                     modern composers like Antonin Dvořák, Edvard Grieg, and Bedřich Smetana. His
                     respective outreach was not limited to Vienna, Austria, and the German-speaking
                     world, but already reached international proportions during Hanslick’s
                     lifetime. The <emph><ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwight%27s_Journal_of_Music">Journal of Music</ref></emph>, edited by the Boston critic John Sullivan
                     Dwight (1813–1893), which appeared between 1852 and 1881 with financial support
                     by the Harvard Musical Association, is particularly representative. Dwight, who
                     shared and occasionally surpassed Hanslick’s classicist conviction, translated
                     a range of Hanslick’s reviews into English, so that between 1866 and 1881 more
                     than three dozen of his essays reached a Boston audience. Hanslick’s reputation
                     was also nourished by his participation in international musical events and
                     in-depth travel reports from, among other places, Bayreuth, London, and Paris
                     to the United States, which he visited in 1890 (see, for example, his reports
                     in <emph>Neue Freie Presse</emph>, <ref target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=nfp&amp;datum=18900624&amp;seite=1&amp;zoom=33">June 24</ref>, <ref target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=nfp&amp;datum=18900625&amp;seite=1&amp;zoom=33">June 25</ref>, and <ref target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=nfp&amp;datum=18900729&amp;seite=1&amp;=33">July 29</ref>). These extensive musico-critical activities ultimately
                     resulted in Hanslick acting as part of renowned music juries—this way, for
                     example, he procured state grants for Dvořák between 1874 and 1877— and
                     repeatedly attending international exhibitions as a correspondent and later as
                     an Austrian delegate, for example at the World’s Fairs in London (1862), Paris
                     (1867), and Vienna (1873).</p>
               </div>
               <div type="inline">
                  <p>While Hanslick’s prominence among the musical public is closely linked to his
                     critiques and the figure of Wagner, his continuing importance in philosophy and
                     musicology depends on other aspects of his work: In 1856, Hanslick was
                     appointed lecturer for the “History and Aesthetics of Musical Art,” the
                     earliest such position not only in Vienna but rather in the entire
                     German-speaking world. Although music history has been taught at universities
                     since the eighteenth century, until then teaching music history was for the
                     most part tantamount to the post of a practical music director. The
                     theoretically oriented lectureship of Hanslick, who was appointed associate
                     professor in 1861 and full professor in 1870, was a novelty that is now
                     considered the first professorship of musicology, which has been generally
                     known under that name only since the founding of the <emph><ref target="https://de.wikisource.org/wiki/Vierteljahrsschrift_f%C3%BCr_Musikwissenschaft">Vierteljahrsschrift für Musikwissenschaft</ref></emph> (Musicology
                     Quarterly; 1885). (On the history of the discipline in Vienna, see <ref target="https://musikwissenschaft.univie.ac.at/ueber-uns/institutsgeschichte/chronik/">this link</ref>.) In 1869, Hanslick published volume 1 of <emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb10598665?page=4,5">Geschichte des Concertwesens in Wien</ref></emph> (History of the Vienna
                     Concert Scene), which could be considered a pioneering achievement in the
                     sociology of music, as his only historical work in a narrow sense. Later books
                     are composed primarily of collected reviews, reports, and essays that Hanslick
                     wanted to be understood as a living history of music in Vienna and as
                     “aesthetic statistics of opera” (<ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11081548?page=8,9"><emph>Die Moderne Oper</emph>, 1:vi</ref>). In <emph>Music, Criticism,
                        and the Challenge of History</emph> (Oxford University Press 2008, chap. 2),
                     Kevin Karnes has framed this approach with regard to Dilthey, Droysen, and
                     Burckhardt as an early attempt at particularistic historiography, which,
                     however, did not prevail historically against philological musicology as
                     developed by Friedrich Chrysander, Otto Jahn, and Philipp Spitta, among others.
                     Even if Hanslick’s relevance for the genesis of academic musicology is for the
                     most part underestimated, his importance as a founder of the discipline
                     nevertheless clearly falls short of his successor Guido Adler, who established
                     the Department of Musicology in Vienna in 1901 and shaped the methodology of
                     the discipline for many years with his essay “<ref target="https://archive.org/details/vierteljahrssch23unkngoog/page/n12/mode/2up">Umfang, Methode und Ziel der Musikwissenschaft</ref>” (<ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/768355">Scope, Method, and Aim of
                        Musicology</ref>) of 1885. </p>
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="images/csm_Alte_Universitaet_Wien_39f321d9a4.jpg"/>
                        <head>The former venue of the University of Vienna, ca. 1850; by courtesy of <ref target="https://onb.digital/result/BAG_12352553">Österreichische Nationalbibliothek</ref></head>
                     </figure>
               </div>
               <div type="inline">
                  <figure>
                     <graphic url="images/csm_VMS_1854_43ca3476ef.jpg"/>
                     <head>Cover of von Eduard Hanslick’s treatise <ref target="https://archive.org/details/VomMusikalischSchnen1tea1854/mode/2up"><emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>, 1st edition, 1854</ref></head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>In addition to Hanslick’s roles as a music critic and professor of the “History
                     and Aesthetics of Musical Art,” his name remains closely associated with a book
                     he wrote at the age of only 29: <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen: Ein Beitrag zur
                        Revision der Aesthetik der Tonkunst</emph> or <emph>On the Musically
                        Beautiful: A Contribution to the Revision of the Aesthetics of Musical
                        Art</emph>. This book, which went through ten revised editions during
                     Hanslick’s lifetime (see the index of Eduard Hanslick’s writings below), can be
                     characterized without exaggeration as the most impactful musico-aesthetic
                     treatise of the nineteenth century, whose central assertions continue to inform
                     debates in aesthetics. <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> (<emph>VMS</emph>
                     for short) develops a perspective specifically derived from the intrinsic
                     properties of musical material, whose focus on the object, critical stance
                     against metaphysical speculation, and up-to-date definition of the problem of
                     music and emotion—reminiscent of the twentieth-century cognitivist concept of
                     emotion—continue to be relevant to contemporary discourse. Historically
                     speaking, particular importance was attributed to Hanslick’s much-cited
                     rejection of the “rotten aesthetics of feeling”—a phrase found only in the
                     preface to the first edition (<ref target="https://archive.org/details/VomMusikalischSchnen1tea1854/page/n1/mode/2up">p. v</ref>)—which, like the analogy between the content of music and the
                     moving arabesque, and the notorious catchphrase that “the content of music is
                        <emph>sonically moved forms</emph>” (Rothfarb and Landerer, <emph>On the
                        Musically Beautiful</emph>, 41), shape Hanslick's reception to the present
                     day. Here, too, the radiance of Hanslick’s treatise, which its translator
                     Geoffrey Payzant, for example, deemed the “founding document of musical
                     aesthetics as we know it” (<emph>Hanslick on the Musically Beautiful: Sixteen
                        Lectures on the Musical Aesthetics of Eduard Hanslick</emph>, Christchurch:
                     Cybereditions 2002, 17), rapidly outgrew German-language discourse. The
                     reputation of <emph>VMS</emph> as a pamphlet directed primarily against Richard
                     Wagner—a reputation undoubtably encouraged in the prefaces of later editions
                     (as was already evident from Hanslick’s polemic against Wagner’s “infinite
                     melody”) and certainly not detrimental to the popularity of this book—clearly
                     falls short, however, and also does not do full justice to Hanslick’s
                     impact.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="inline">
                  <p>The reception of Hanslick’s writings markedly exceeds his own epoch and, with
                     regard to music philosophy and musicology, encompasses such central figures as
                     Guido Adler, Friedrich Nietzsche, Heinrich Schenker, and Ludwig Wittgenstein.
                     Generally speaking, the impact of <emph>VMS</emph>, which stretches from the
                     beginnings of academic music research to numerous composers (Pfitzner,
                     Schoenberg, Stravinsky) and established philosophers like Theodor W. Adorno,
                     Karl Popper, and Roman Ingarden, has hardly been researched systematically up
                     to this point. Respective research literature is mostly limited to passing
                     references regarding certain analogies between Hanslick and later authors,
                     which often remain vague and do not seriously examine reception-historical
                     correlations. There are notable parallels between Hanslick’s treatise and the
                     late philosophy of Wittgenstein, for example, who determined the meaning of a
                     piece of music to be specifically musical and decidedly rejected the idea that
                     music could be successfully verbalized. While these contexts have hardly been
                     explored, Nietzsche’s relationship to Hanslick from his <emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb10999253?page=4,5">Geburt der Tragödie aus dem Geiste der Musik</ref></emph> (The Birth of
                     Tragedy Out of the Spirit of Music, 1872) to his late works—<emph>Der Fall
                        Wagner </emph> (The Case of Wagner, 1888); <emph>Nietzsche contra
                        Wagner</emph> (1889)—, which takes a reserved approach to Wagner, has often
                     been the subject of research. Furthermore, OMB fell on particularly fertile
                     ground with analytical philosophy of music and its focus on the relationship
                     between emotion and music as well as its distinctly objective orientation.
                     Although Hanslick already played a major role in the context of Susanne K.
                     Langer’s <emph>Philosophy in a New Key</emph> (1942), <emph>VMS</emph> moved to
                     the center of the debate around the 1980s. This development depends primarily
                     on the relevance of the cognitivist concept of emotion in analytical discourse
                     on music, which is laid out expressis verbis in <emph>VMS</emph> and attracted
                     the attention of contemporary philosophers such as Malcolm Budd, Peter Kivy,
                     and Stephen Davies. (A detailed analysis of Hanslick’s reception in the
                     English-speaking world can be found under <ref target="https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctvktrwbs">this link</ref>). Although no
                     modern aesthetic theorist is in complete agreement with Hanslick’s position,
                     his framing of issues like—among others—the relation of music to affect states
                     (feelings, emotions, moods, etc.), the autonomy of the “work of art,” or the
                     aesthetic significance of musical facture has had lasting impact and continues
                     to influence respective debates to this day.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <graphic url="images/csm_Collage_Rezeption_26b56785ee.jpg"/>
                     <head>Collage of images of <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guido_Adler_(Musikwissenschaftler)#/media/Datei:GuidoAdler.png">Adler</ref>, <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedrich_Nietzsche#/media/Datei:Nietzsche187a.jpg">Nietzsche</ref>, <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinrich_Schenker#/media/Datei:Hermann_Clemens_Kosel_Heinrich_Schenker_1912.jpg">Schenker</ref>, and <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludwig_Wittgenstein#/media/Datei:Ludwig_Wittgenstein_(cropped).jpg">Wittgenstein</ref> (Wikipedia Creative Commons)</head>
                  </figure>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="sub">
               <head>Eduard Hanslick’s Writings</head>
               <div type="block">
                  <list type="bibl">
                     <item>“Ueber den subjektiven Eindruck der Musik und seine Stellung in der
                        Aesthetik,” <emph>Oesterreichische Blätter für Literatur und Kunst</emph>
                        <ref target="https://books.google.de/books?id=-cFLAAAAcAAJ&amp;hl=de&amp;pg=PA177#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">30 (1853), 177–178;</ref>
                        <ref target="https://books.google.de/books?id=-cFLAAAAcAAJ&amp;hl=de&amp;pg=PA181#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">31 (1853), 181–182</ref>; <ref target="https://books.google.de/books?id=-cFLAAAAcAAJ&amp;hl=de&amp;pg=PA193#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">33 (1853), 193–195</ref>.</item>
                     <item><ref target="https://books.google.de/books?id=kMlLAAAAcAAJ&amp;hl=de&amp;pg=PA78#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">“Die Tonkunst in ihren Beziehungen zur
                           Natur,”</ref> <emph>Oesterreichische Blätter für Literatur und
                           Kunst</emph> 11 (1854), 78–80.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://archive.org/details/VomMusikalischSchnen1tea1854/mode/2up">Vom Musikalisch-Schönen: Ein Beitrag zur Revision der Aesthetik der
                              Tonkunst</ref></emph>, Leipzig: Rudolph Weigel, 1854. Further
                        editions: <list>
                           <item><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb10598668?page=6,7">2nd edition</ref>, Leipzig: Rudolph Weigel, 1858.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb10598670?page=6,7">3rd edition</ref>, Leipzig: Rudolph Weigel, 1865.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=x6y6ZcYzYpsC&amp;dq=eduard%20hanslick%20vom%20musikalisch-sch%C3%B6nen%201874&amp;hl=de&amp;pg=PP5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">4th edition</ref>, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1874.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=xP0I3i3ALK4C&amp;dq=eduard%20hanslick%20vom%20musikalisch-sch%C3%B6nen%201876&amp;hl=de&amp;pg=PR3#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">5th edition</ref>, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1876.</item>
                           <item>6. Auflage, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1881.</item>
                           <item>7. Auflage, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1885.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://archive.org/details/beautifulinmusic1891hans/page/n3/mode/2up">8th edition</ref>, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1891.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://archive.org/details/vommusikalischs00hansgoog/page/n4/mode/2up">9th edition</ref>, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1896.</item>
                           <item><ref target="https://archive.org/details/VomMusikalischSchnen10tea1902/mode/2up">10th edition</ref>, Leipzig: Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1902.</item>
                        </list></item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb10598665?page=4,5">Geschichte des Concertwesens in Wien</ref></emph>, Vienna: Wilhelm
                        Braumüller, 1869.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11727302?page=,1">Geschichte des Concertwesens in Wien</ref></emph>, vol 2, <emph>Aus
                           dem Concertsaal: Kritiken und Schilderungen aus den letzten 20 Jahren des
                           Wiener Musiklebens nebst einem Anhang, Musikalische Reisebriefe aus
                           England, Frankreich und der Schweiz</emph>, Vienna: Wilhelm Braumüller,
                        1870.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11081548?page=4,5">Die moderne Oper: Kritiken und Studien</ref></emph>, Berlin: A.
                        Hofmann, 1875.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11727297?page=8,9">Musikalische Stationen: Neue Folge der “Modernen Oper”</ref></emph>,
                        Berlin: A. Hofmann, 1880.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11556958?page=8,9">Aus dem Opernleben der Gegenwart: Der “Modernen Oper” III. Theil;
                              Neue Kritiken und Studien</ref></emph>, Berlin: A. Hofmann,
                        1884.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11556962?page=8,9">Suite: Aufsätze über Musik und Musiker</ref></emph>, Vienna: Franz
                        Prochaska, 1884.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11556956?page=8,9">Concerte, Componisten und Virtuosen der letzten fünfzehn Jahre, 1870–1885: Kritiken</ref></emph>, Berlin: Allgemeiner Verein für deutsche Literatur, 1886.</item>
                     <item><ref target="https://austria-forum.org/web-books/kpwde01de1886onb/00000138">“Die Musik in Wien,”</ref> in <emph>Die österreichisch-ungarische
                           Monarchie in Wort und Bild</emph>, vol. 1, <emph>Wien und
                           Niederösterreich</emph>, ed. by crown prince archduke Rudolf, Vienna:
                        Druck und Verlag der k. u. k. Hof- und Staatsdruckerei, 1886,
                        123–138.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://archive.org/details/musikalischessk00hansgoog/page/n8/mode/2up">Musikalisches Skizzenbuch: Der “Modernen Oper” IV. Theil; Neue
                              Kritiken und Schilderungen</ref></emph>, Berlin: Allgemeiner Verein
                        für deutsche Litteratur, 1888.</item>
                     <item><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11472059?q=%28eduard+hanslick+Wien+1848%E2%80%931888%29&amp;page=312,313">“Musik,”</ref> in <emph>Wien 1848–1888: Denkschrift zum 2. December
                           1888</emph>, ed. by the Vienna City Council, Vienna: Carl Konegen, 1888,
                        2:301–342.</item>
                     <item><ref target="https://austria-forum.org/web-books/kpwde04de1888onb/00000265">“Volksmusik, Dialect und Dialectpoesie,”</ref> in <emph>Die
                           österreichisch-ungarische Monarchie in Wort und Bild</emph>, vol. 2,
                           <emph>Niederösterreich</emph>, ed. by crown prince archduke Rudolf,
                        Vienna: Druck und Verlag der k. u. k. Hof- und Staatsdruckerei, 1888,
                        251–262 (in collaboration with Richard von Muth).</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11556960?page=4,5">Musikalisches und Litterarisches: Der “Modernen Oper” V. Theil;
                              Kritiken und Schilderungen</ref></emph>, Berlin: Allgemeiner Verein
                        für deutsche Litteratur, 1889.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11556961?page=10,11">Aus dem Tagebuche eines Musikers: Der “Modernen Oper” VI. Theil;
                              Kritiken und Schilderungen</ref></emph>, Berlin: Allgemeiner Verein
                        für deutsche Litteratur, 1892.</item>
                     <item><emph>Aus meinem Leben</emph>, Berlin: Allgemeiner Verein für deutsche
                        Litteratur, 1894, <ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11573682?page=6,7">vol. 1</ref> and <ref target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb11557245?page=12,13">vol. 2</ref>.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_Yh1NAAAAMAAJ/page/n7/mode/2up">Fünf Jahre Musik, 1891–1895: Der “Modernen Oper” VII. Theil;
                              Kritiken</ref></emph>, Berlin: Allgemeiner Verein für deutsche
                        Litteratur, 1896.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://archive.org/details/amendedesjahrhun08hans/page/n3/mode/2up">Am Ende des Jahrhunderts, 1895–1899: Der “Modernen Oper” VIII. Teil;
                              Musikalische Kritiken und Schilderungen</ref></emph>, Berlin:
                        Allgemeiner Verein für deutsche Litteratur, 1899.</item>
                     <item><emph><ref target="https://archive.org/details/ausneuerundneue00hansgoog/page/n5/mode/2up">Aus neuer und neuerster Zeit: Der “Modernen Oper” IX. Teil;
                              Musikalische Kritiken und Schilderungen</ref></emph>, Berlin:
                        Allgemeiner Verein für deutsche Litteratur, 1900.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="block">
                  <head>English-Language Translations of Hanslick's Writings</head>
                  <div type="block">
                     <list type="bibl">
                        <item><emph><ref target="https://archive.org/details/beautifulinmusic00hans"
                                 >The Beautiful in Music: A Contribution to the Revisal of Musical
                                 Aesthetics</ref></emph>, trans. by Gustav Cohen, London: Novello
                           and Company, 1891.</item>
                        <item><emph>Vienna’s Golden Years of Music, 1850–1900</emph>, trans. by Henry Pleasants, New York: Simon and Schuster, 1950.</item>
                        <item><emph>The Beautiful in Music: A Contribution to the Revisal of Musical Aesthetics</emph>, 2nd ed., trans. by Gustav Cohen, ed. by Morris Weitz, Indianapolis: Bobbs-Merrill Publishing, 1957.</item>
                        <item><emph>Eduard Hanslick: Music Criticisms 1846–1899</emph>, 2nd ed., trans. by Henry Pleasants, London: Penguin Books, 1963.</item>
                        <item><emph>On the Musically Beautiful: A Contribution Towards the Revision of the Aesthetics of Music</emph>, trans. by Geoffrey Payzant, Indianapolis: Hackett Publishing, 1986.</item>
                        <item><emph>Hanslickʼs Music Criticisms</emph>, trans. by Henry Pleasants, New York: Dover Publications, 1988.</item>
                        <item>“Eduard Hanslick: Brahms’s Newest Instrumental Compositions (1889),” trans. by Susan Gillespie, in <emph>Brahms and His World</emph>, ed. by Walter Frisch, Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1990, 145–150.</item>
                        <item>“Eduard Hanslick: Memories and Letters,” trans. by Susan Gillespie, in <emph>Brahms and His World</emph>, ed. by Walter Frisch, Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1990, 163–184.</item>
                        <item>“Hanslick contra Wagner: ‘The Ring Cycle Comes to Vienna’ and ‘Parsifal Literature,’” trans. by Thomas Grey, in <emph>Richard Wagner and His World</emph>, ed. by Thomas Grey, Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2009, 409–425.</item>
                        <item><emph>Eduard Hanslick’s ‘On the Musically Beautiful’: A New Translation</emph>, trans. by Lee Rothfarb and Christoph Landerer, Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </div> 
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
