<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hanslick Online - Editorial Conventions and How to Cite</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName resp="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1226158307">Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bäckerstraße 13</addrLine>
               <addrLine>1010 Vienna</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2023">2023</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <body xml:lang="en-US">
         <div type="main">
            <head>Editorial Conventions and How to Cite</head>
            <byline>Alexander Wilfing and Meike Wilfing-Albrecht</byline>
            <div type="sub">
               <head>Editorial Conventions</head>
               <p>This edition is based on the ten editions of Eduard Hanslick’s treatise <emph>Vom
                     Musikalisch-Schönen: Ein Beitrag zur Revision der Ästhetik der Tonkunst</emph>
                     (<emph>On the Musically Beautiful: A Contribution towards the Revision of the
                     Aesthetics of Music</emph>), published between 1854 and 1902 in occasionally
                  revised textual versions. Whereas editions 1 to 3 (1854–1865) were published by
                  Rudolph Weigel (Leipzig), Johann Ambrosius Barth (Leipzig) produced the treatise
                  from edition 4 onward (1874–1902). Other sources, like sketches, setting copies,
                  proof copies, etc., are no longer known today, since Hanslick’s estate was lost
                  during the Second World War. The printed copies are thus the only available
                  templates for our digital edition. The articles or chapters from which this
                  treatise presumably originates, some of which were published in advance (see the
                  first two entries under “<ref target="bedeutung-hanslick-engl.html?lang=en">Eduard
                     Hanslick’s Writings</ref>”), did not figure into this edition.</p>
               <p>The editions of the original treatise—transcribed and corrected by Meike
                  Wilfing-Albrecht—are reproduced as faithfully as possible; the spelling is
                  retained. Errors that were corrected by Hanslick himself within the editions—e.g.,
                  the change from “psychisch” (psychic) to “physisch” (physical), 2.13, from edition
                  9 onward—are also reproduced faithfully. Only evident errata (e.g., “Mnsik”
                  instead of “Musik,” 5.6, in edition 3) have been corrected without indication.
                  Paragraphs are maintained (except for in poems), and changes between editions are
                  indicated by the following markers: contraction → &amp;; subdivision → a and b;
                  addition → 3rd decimal place; deletion → number gap. A revised collation feature
                  is currently being developed. Page numbers and breaks can either be shown or
                  masked via the “Annotations” menu. Verse breaks are indicated by slashes /. We
                  have converted the footnotes to endnotes with jump marks and numbered them
                  consecutively instead of using the original asterisks * to provide a more precise
                  attribution. Up to edition 7, the headings of individual chapters were only
                  displayed in the table of contents. For purposes of manageable navigation, we have
                  incorporated them into the transcription of editions 1–7.</p>
               <p>The printed copies of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> contain several fonts,
                  the meticulous reproduction of which, however, did not seem sensible for a digital
                  edition. The German main text is set in Fraktur script throughout, while Latin,
                  French, Italian, or English passages are usually produced in Latin typeface
                  (especially prominent in the extended original French quotation in 2.43, but also,
                  for example, in “Dr.” on the title page). Since this difference in typeface has no
                  semantic relevance, the present edition refrains from any respective visual
                  demarcation. Text passages formatted in bold face, however, are reproduced
                  according to the templates (cf. 1.31). In the original, moreover, textual emphases
                  are marked with spaced letters, which have been turned into italics for our online
                  edition.</p>
               <p>The music examples shown in chapters 2.19, 2.25 and 2.28 (edition 1), as well as
                  2.19 and 2.17 (editions 2–10), have been typeset anew and arranged according to
                  the original template by our colleague Vasiliki Papadopoulou, for which we thank
                  her sincerely. Only the bracket breaks diverge from the original, as they are only
                  due to the smaller printing format of the respective hard copy and thus have no
                  semantic validity. Hanslick probably had the musical examples set for this
                  specific purpose, but their print templates are not known either. In the example
                  of Christoph Willibald Gluck’s “Che farò” (2.27, from edition 2 onward), the
                  deviations in syllable division between editions are not indicated separately.
                  These can be checked against the respective facsimile reproduction. </p>
               <p>The TEI annotation of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> was provided by
                  Alexander Wilfing, who oversaw the entire edition process. In a first step, names,
                  works, and places were marked up as entities, each of which can be color-coded in
                  the online edition via the “Annotations” menu. In the index—where <ref
                     target="listperson.html?lang=en">persons</ref> (historical as well as
                  fictional) and <ref target="listbibl.html?lang=en">works</ref> are further linked
                  with each other—and the detailed information of annotations, we used the spelling
                  of the <ref target="https://lobid.org/gnd">GND</ref> data base for person names
                  (if available in each case) and that of <ref target="https://www.geonames.org/"
                     >GeoNames</ref> for place names. In the case of names and places, only names
                  and places themselves and terms directly related to them are marked, not groups of
                  people that have such references. For example, “Griechenland” (“Greece”) and
                  “griechisch” (“Greek”) are annotated, “Griechen” (“Greeks”), however, are not,
                  which then also applies to “Gluck” and “Piccini”, as opposed to “Gluckisten”
                  (“Gluckists”) and “Piccinisten” (“Piccinists”) (2.43). Such terms can of course be
                  found via a <ref target="search-engl.html?lang=en">full-text search</ref>. The
                  logo of “Hanslick Online” was designed by Olivia Reichl.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub">
               <head>How to Cite</head>
               <p>Eduard Hanslick, <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen: Ein Beitrag zur Revision der
                     Ästhetik der Tonkunst</emph>, ed. by Alexander Wilfing in collaboration with
                  Meike Wilfing-Albrecht (2023), edition number, paragraph number, hyperlink. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
