<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hanslick Online - Editionsrichtlinien und How to Cite</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName resp="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1226158307">Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bäckerstraße 13</addrLine>
               <addrLine>1010 Vienna</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2023">2023</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <body xml:lang="en-US">
         <div type="main">
            <head>Editorial Conventions and How to Cite</head>
            <byline>Alexander Wilfing und Meike Wilfing-Albrecht</byline>
            <div type="sub">
               <head>Editorial Conventions</head>
               <p>This edition is based on the ten editions of Eduard Hanslick’s treatise <emph>Vom
                     Musikalisch-Schönen: Ein Beitrag zur Revision der Ästhetik der Tonkunst</emph>
                     (<emph>On the Musically Beautiful: A Contribution towards the Revision of the
                     Aesthetics of Musical Art</emph>), published between 1854 and 1902 in
                  occasionally revised textual versions. Whereas editions 1 to 3 (1854–1865) were
                  published by Rudolph Weigel (Leipzig), Johann Ambrosius Barth (Leipzig) produced
                  the treatise from edition 4 onward (1874–1902). Other sources like sketches,
                  setting copies, proof copies, etc., are not known as of today, since Hanslick’s
                  estate has been lost during the Second World War. The printed copies thus are the
                  only available templates for our digital edition. The articles or chapters from
                  which this treatise presumably originates and which were partly published in
                  advance (see the first two entries under „<ref
                     target="bedeutung-hanslick-engl.html">Eduard Hanslick Schriften</ref>“) did not
                  figure into this edition.</p>
               <p>The editions of the original treatise—transcribed and corrected by Meike
                  Wilfing-Albrecht—are reproduced as faithfully as possible, the spelling is
                  retained. Errors that were corrected by Hanslick himself within the editions—e.g.,
                  the change from „psychisch“ (psychic) to „physisch“ (physical), 2.13, from edition
                  9 onward—are also reproduced faithfully. Only evident errata (e.g., „Mnsik“
                  instead of „Musik,“ 5.6, in edition 3) have been corrected without indication.
                  Paragraphs are maintained (except for poems) and numbered by taking edition 1 as
                  the point of origin. Modified paragraphs between editions are indicated by the
                  following markers: contraction → &amp;; subdivision → a and b; addition → 3rd
                  decimal place; deletion → number gap. Page numbers and breaks can either be shown
                  or masked by using the „annotations“ menu. Verse breaks are indicated by using
                  slashes /. The footnotes have been converted to endnotes with jump marks and have
                  been numbered consecutively instead of using the original asterisks * to provide a
                  more precise attribution Up to edition 7, the headings of individual chapters were
                  only displayed in the table of contents. For the purpose of manageable navigation,
                  they were incorporated into the transcription of editions 1-7. </p>
               <p>The printed copies of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> contain several fonts,
                  the meticulous reproduction of which, however, did not seem sensible for the
                  purpose of a digital edition. The German main text is set in Fraktur script
                  throughout, while Latin, French, Italian, or English passages are usually produced
                  in Latin typeface (especially prominent in the extended original French quotation
                  in 2.43, but also, for example, in „Dr.“ on the title page). Since this difference
                  in typeface has no semantic relevance, the present edition refrains from any
                  respective visual demarcation. Text passages formatted in bold face, however, are
                  reproduced according to the templates (cf. 1.31). In the original, moreover,
                  textual emphases are marked with spaced letters, which have been turned into
                  italics for our online edition.</p>
               <p>The music examples shown in chapters 2.19, 2.25, 2.28 (edition 1) as well as 2.19
                  and 2.17 (editions 2–10) have been typeset anew and arranged according to the
                  original template by our colleague Vasiliki Papadopoulou, for which we thank her
                  sincerely. Only the bracket breaks diverge from the original, as they are only due
                  to the smaller printing format of the respective hard copy and thus have no
                  semantic validity. Hanslick probably had the musical examples set for this
                  specific purpose, but their print templates are not known either. In the example
                  of Christoph Willibald Gluck’s „Che farò“ (2.27, from edition 2 onward), the
                  deviations in syllable division between editions are not indicated separately.
                  These can be checked against the respective facsimile reproduction. </p>
               <p>The TEI annotation of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> was provided by
                  Alexander Wilfing, who oversaw the entire edition process. In a first step, names,
                  works, and places were marked up as entities, each of which can be color-coded in
                  the online edition by using the „annotations“ menu. In the index—where <ref
                     target="https://hanslick-online.github.io/hsl-app/listperson.html">persons</ref>
                  (historical as well as fictional) and <ref
                     target="https://hanslick-online.github.io/hsl-app/listbibl.html">works</ref>
                  are further linked with each other—and the detailed information of annotations,
                  the spelling of the <ref target="https://lobid.org/gnd">GND</ref> data base was
                  used for person names (if available in each case), and that of <ref
                     target="https://www.geonames.org/">GeoNames</ref> for place names. In the case
                  of names / places, only names / places themselves and terms which are directly
                  related to names / places were marked, but not groups of people that have such
                  references. For example, „Griechenland“ („Greece“) and „griechisch“ („Greek“) are
                  annotated, „Griechen“ („Greeks“), however, are not, which then also applies to
                  „Gluck“ and „Piccini“, as opposed to „Gluckisten“ („Gluckists“) and „Piccinisten“
                  („Piccinists“) (2.43). Such terms can, of course, be found via <ref
                     target="https://hanslick-online.github.io/hsl-app/search.html">full-text
                     search</ref>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub">
               <head>How to Cite</head>
               <p>Eduard Hanslick, <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen: Ein Beitrag zur Revision der
                     Ästhetik der Tonkunst</emph>, ed by Alexander Wilfing in collaboration with
                  Meike Wilfing-Albrecht and Christoph Landerer (2023), edition number, paragraph
                  number, hyperlink. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
