<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hanslick Online - Editorial Conventions and How to Cite</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName resp="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1226158307">Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bäckerstraße 13</addrLine>
               <addrLine>1010 Vienna</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2023">2024</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body xml:lang="en-US">
         <div type="main">
            <head>Editorial Conventions and How to Cite</head>
            <p>As of the end of 2024, the website “Hanslick Online” provides three distinct textual
               corpora related to Eduard Hanslick:<list>
                  <item>an edition of all ten versions of Hanslick’s aesthetic treatise <emph>Vom
                        Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>, ed. by Alexander Wilfing in collaboration with
                     Meike Wilfing-Albrecht and Daniel Elsner (2023),</item>
                  <item>an edition of Hanslick’s writings for the <hi rend="italic">Neue Freie
                        Presse</hi>, ed. by Alexander Wilfing in collaboration of Katharina Bamer,
                     Daniel Elsner, and Anna-Maria Pfiel (2023–2025), and</item>
                  <item>an edition of reviews of the initial edition of <emph>Vom
                        Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>, ed. by Alexander Wilfing in collaboration with
                     Daniel Elsner and Anna-Maria Pfiel (2024–2025).</item>
               </list></p>
            <p>The Editions were / are led by Alexander Wilfing, with Daniel Elsner overseeing their
               technical realization. The logo of “Hanslick Online” was designed by Olivia Reichl.
               David Heyde proofread the English version of explanatory texts in 2023. The
               recommended format of citation for each text corpus is as follows:<list>
                  <item>Eduard Hanslick, <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen: Ein Beitrag zur Revision der
                        Ästhetik der Tonkunst</emph>, ed. by Alexander Wilfing in collaboration with
                     Meike Wilfing-Albrecht and Daniel Elsner (2023), edition number, paragraph
                     number, hyperlink.</item>
                  <item>Eduard Hanslick, “Title: Subtitle,” in <emph>Neue Freie Presse</emph>, No. /
                     Date, ed. by Alexander Wilfing in collaboration with Katharina Bamer,
                     Anna-Maria Pfiel, and Daniel Elsner (2023–2025), hyperlink.</item>
                  <item>Author, „Title: Subtitle“, in <emph>Journal</emph>, No. / Date, ed. by
                     Alexander Wilfing in collaboration with Anna-Maria Pfiel and Daniel Elsner
                     (2024–2025), Hyperlink.</item>
               </list></p>
            <div type="sub">
               <head>Editorial Conventions (<hi rend="italic">Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</hi>)</head>
               <byline>Alexander Wilfing and Meike Wilfing-Albrecht, 2023</byline>
               <p>This edition is based on the ten versions of Eduard Hanslick’s aesthetic treatise
                     <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen: Ein Beitrag zur Revision der Ästhetik der
                     Tonkunst</emph> (<emph>On the Musically Beautiful: A Contribution towards the
                     Revision of the Aesthetics of Music</emph>), published between 1854 and 1902 in
                  occasionally revised textual versions. Whereas editions 1 to 3 (1854–1865) were
                  published by Rudolph Weigel (Leipzig), Johann Ambrosius Barth (Leipzig) produced
                  the treatise from edition 4 onward (1874–1902). Other sources, like sketches,
                  setting copies, proof copies, etc., are no longer known today, since Hanslick’s
                  estate was lost during the Second World War. The printed copies are thus the only
                  available templates for our digital edition. The articles or chapters from which
                  this treatise presumably originates, some of which were published in advance (see
                  the first two entries under “<ref target="bedeutung-hanslick-engl.html?lang=en"
                     >Eduard Hanslick’s Writings</ref>”), did not figure into this edition (they
                  will be provided as part of a newly granted research project).</p>
               <p>The editions of the original treatise—transcribed and corrected by Meike
                  Wilfing-Albrecht—are reproduced as faithfully as possible; the spelling is
                  retained. Errors that were corrected by Hanslick himself within the editions—e.g.,
                  the change from “psychisch” (psychic) to “physisch” (physical), 2.13, from edition
                  9 onward—are also reproduced faithfully. Only evident errata (e.g., “Mnsik”
                  instead of “Musik,” 5.6, in edition 3) have been corrected without indication.
                  Paragraphs are maintained (except for in poems), and changes between editions are
                  indicated by the following markers: contraction → &amp;; subdivision → a and b;
                  addition → 3rd decimal place; deletion → number gap. A revised collation feature
                  is currently being developed. Page numbers and breaks can either be shown or
                  masked via the “Annotations” menu. Verse breaks are indicated by slashes /. We
                  have converted the footnotes to endnotes with jump marks and numbered them
                  consecutively instead of using the original asterisks * to provide a more precise
                  attribution. Up to edition 7, the headings of individual chapters were only
                  displayed in the table of contents. For purposes of manageable navigation, we have
                  incorporated them into the transcription of editions 1–7.</p>
               <p>The printed copies of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> contain several fonts,
                  the meticulous reproduction of which, however, did not seem sensible for a digital
                  edition. The German main text is set in Fraktur script throughout, while Latin,
                  French, Italian, or English passages are usually produced in Latin typeface
                  (especially prominent in the extended original French quotation in 2.43, but also,
                  for example, in “Dr.” on the title page). Since this difference in typeface has no
                  semantic relevance, the present edition refrains from any respective visual
                  demarcation. Text passages formatted in bold face, however, are reproduced
                  according to the templates (cf. 1.31). In the original, moreover, textual emphases
                  are marked with spaced letters, which have been turned into italics for our online
                  edition.</p>
               <p>Whereas the facsimiles of editions 1 and 4–10 were digitized and prepared by
                  Alexander Wilfing and Mehmet Emir, the <ref
                     target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de">MDZ</ref> provides premium
                  digital copies of editions 2 and 3. The music examples shown in chapters 2.19,
                  2.25 and 2.28 (edition 1), as well as 2.19 and 2.17 (editions 2–10), have been
                  typeset anew and arranged according to the original template by our colleague
                  Vasiliki Papadopoulou, for which we thank her sincerely. Only the bracket breaks
                  diverge from the original, as they are only due to the smaller printing format of
                  the respective hard copy and thus have no semantic validity. Hanslick probably had
                  the musical examples set for this specific purpose, but their print templates are
                  not known either. In the example of Christoph Willibald Gluck’s “Che farò” (2.27,
                  from edition 2 onward), the deviations in syllable division between editions are
                  not indicated separately. These can be checked against the respective facsimile
                  reproduction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub">
               <head>Editorial Conventions (Hanslick’s Writings for the <hi rend="italic">Neue Freie
                     Presse</hi> and the Reviews of <hi rend="italic">Vom
                  Musikalisch-Schönen</hi>)</head>
               <byline>Alexander Wilfing, 2024</byline>
               <p>The guidelines for the edition of Hanslick’s writings for the <hi rend="italic"
                     >Neue Freie Presse</hi> and the reviews of the initial edition of <emph>Vom
                     Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> for the most part match those specified for his
                  aesthetic treatise. They thus will only be defined insofar as they differ from the
                  principles explicated above. Footnotes are indicated by asterisks * according to
                  the original template, since they occur only rarely and, compared to <hi
                     rend="italic">Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</hi>, as part of shorter essays. </p>
               <p>For now, the edition is based chiefly on Hanslick’s extensive feuilletons “below
                  the line,” clearly marked by the initials “Ed. H.” from 1864 onward, the founding
                  year of <hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</hi>, to 1904, the year of his death.
                  These texts (about 900 items) typically appear in 3 columns on the first 2–3 pages
                  of an issue. Other music-related writings contained in <hi rend="italic">Neue
                     Freie Presse</hi> will then follow, provided Hanslick can be reasonably
                  considered to have authored them. Alexander Wilfing initially created a register
                  of these texts in 2011 as part of Christoph Landerer’s research project
                  “Nietzsche’s Reception of Hanslick” via <ref target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/"
                     >ANNO</ref>, which he later expanded significantly. The digital copies we
                  provide in addition to the TEI/XML text are also obtained from ANNO (Austrian
                  Newspaper Online). For purely pragmatic reasons, the editors proceed in ascending
                  and descending order as regards chronology.</p>
               <p>Wilfing also identified the 26 reviews of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>
                  through various repositories (ANNO, <ref
                     target="https://www.deutsche-digitale-bibliothek.de/newspaper">DZP</ref>, <ref
                     target="https://www.jstor.org/">JSTOR</ref>, etc.) and the appendix of Mark
                  Evan Bonds’s <emph>Absolute Music: The History of an Idea</emph> (Oxford: Oxford
                  University Press, 2014), 301–307. There reviews were published between 1854 and
                  the end of 1857, when the second edition of Hanslick’s aesthetic treatise was
                  released, judging by an advertisement in the <hi rend="italic">Börsenblatt für den
                     Deutschen Buchhandel</hi> (December 14, 1857, 2). The length of these texts
                  varies from brief, single-page reviews to extensive multi-part critiques, such as
                  those by Emil Kuh (<hi rend="italic">Der Humorist</hi>, 18, no. 305, 1219; 18, no.
                  306, 1223; 18, no. 309, 1235), Franz Brendel (<hi rend="italic">Neue Zeitschrift
                     für Musik</hi>, 42, no. 8, 77–82; 42, no. 9, 89–91; 42, no. 10, 97–100), and
                  Ludwig Bischoff (<hi rend="italic">Niederrheinische Musik-Zeitung</hi>, 3, no. 7,
                  49–53; 3, no. 8, 57–60; 3, no. 9, 65–66; 3, no. 10, 73–75).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sub">
               <head>Collection, Selection, and Presentation of Data</head>
               <byline>Alexander Wilfing, 2024</byline>
               <p>The TEI annotation of *Vom Musikalisch-Schönen* was carried out by Alexander
                  Wilfing, who oversaw the entire edition. For the *Neue Freie Presse* writings, he
                  was assisted by Katharina Bamer and Anna-Maria Pfiel, the latter also being
                  responsible for transcribing and annotating reviews from the first edition of *Vom
                  Musikalisch-Schönen*. While the XML/TEI files for the ten editions of Hanslick’s
                  aesthetic treatise were generated from Word documents, the project team utilized
                  Transkribus for the transcription, editing, and annotation of the other corpora.
                  Formatting and final editorial work were completed using the Oxygen XML editor,
                  while "named entities" were captured, linked, and integrated through a Baserow
                  database. The digital edition was implemented using the "DSE Static Cookiecutter"
                  framework developed by ACDH-CH, a static-site generator for XML/TEI-encoded
                  digital editions.</p>
               <p>Due to the large volume of texts—comprising approximately 2,000,000 words—the
                  initial annotation schema focused on (real and fictional) people, works (music,
                  texts, images), and geographical locations. Additional categories of "named
                  entities," such as buildings, groups, and events, may be added in later phases.
                  Users can toggle the display of individual or all entities via the "Annotations"
                  menu. When activated, the annotations appear as icons, with colors that correspond
                  to the types of entities listed in the menu. Clicking on an icon displays
                  essential information about the entity, while more detailed data can be accessed
                  via the "Further Details" link. These detailed pages can be reached either
                  directly from the edited texts or through the indexes of persons, works, and
                  places, offering both data and a summary of mentions of each entity in Hanslick’s
                  writings.</p>
               <p>Currently, the following datasets are being compiled:</p>
               <p>For locations, both the current name in the local language(s) and the name used by
                  Hanslick are recorded. Standard data identifiers such as the GeoNames URI are
                  included. Additional datasets (Wikidata, GND, geographical coordinates, etc.) are
                  automatically added through a GitHub action set up by Daniel Elsner. All names are
                  transliterated into Latin script, and a "Checked" tag indicates whether the data
                  has been verified following the four-eyes principle.</p>
               <p>For fictional characters, both the original names and those used by Hanslick are
                  listed, and each figure is linked to the relevant work entry. Multiple linkages
                  are avoided—for example, there are six separate entities named "Faust" from works
                  by Berlioz, Boito, Goethe, Gounod, Spohr, and Schumann—allowing for greater
                  transparency in the statistical evaluation of "named entities." For deities and
                  mythological figures mentioned independently of specific works, available
                  authority data (GND and Wikidata) is included.</p>
               <p>For real persons, we record the spelling according to GND along with Hanslick’s
                  variations. We also manually capture life dates, up to three professions or roles,
                  and significant activities. Birthdates and biographical details (where available)
                  are drawn from widely used encyclopedias such as the ÖML, ÖBL, PMB, MGG, Grove,
                  and the Lexicon of the Sophie Drinker Institute. Additional datasets (Wikidata and
                  links to ÖML, ÖBL, and PMB) are added automatically via a GitHub action.</p>
               <p>For works, we follow the same method, listing both the original and Hanslick’s
                  variations of titles. Works are linked to their creators, as well as to the
                  figures and sections referenced by Hanslick. Autonomous sections (e.g., a song
                  from a cycle) are recorded separately, but movements from a sonata are linked to
                  the entire sonata. Additional datasets include GND numbers and links to freely
                  accessible digital copies (IMSLP, MDZ, DTA, archive.org, or Google Books if no
                  other source is available).</p>
               <p>The main goal of the *Criticism Project* is to produce a digital edition of
                  Hanslick’s writings for the *Neue Freie Presse* to facilitate the analysis of
                  specific topics. Due to resource constraints, the identification of every
                  individual and work is limited. If a "named entity" cannot be definitively
                  identified, it is marked with the note "unclear reference." Ambiguous work
                  references—such as Schubert’s "A minor sonata," mentioned by Hanslick on December
                  1, 1864, where it is unclear whether he refers to D537, D784, or D845—are
                  displayed through multiple linked entities, up to a maximum of five. Feedback on
                  errors and gaps is always welcome.</p>
               <p>The inclusion of variant spellings for names and works ensures that, for example,
                  Niccolò Piccinni—whom Hanslick refers to as "Picinni" or "Piccini"—and Offenbach’s
                  *Les Géorgiennes*—which Hanslick calls "Die Georgierinnern," "Die schönen
                  Georgierinnen," or "Die schönen Weiber von Georgien"—can be found via the index.
                  For names and locations, only the names themselves or terms with a direct
                  reference to them are annotated, not groups associated with them. For instance,
                  "Griechenland" and "griechisch" are annotated, but "Greeks" are not, just as
                  "Gluck" and "Piccini" are annotated, but not "Gluckists" or "Piccinists" (2.43).
                  Such terms are discoverable through full-text search. Further categories of "named
                  entities" (buildings, groups, events, etc.) are planned, pending additional
                  funding.</p>
               <p>The TEI annotation of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> was provided by
                  Alexander Wilfing, who oversaw the entire edition process. </p>
               <p>and transcribed, proofread, and partially annotated with the help of <ref
                     target="https://readcoop.eu/de/transkribus/">Transkribus</ref>. Formatting and
                  editorial finishing touches are performed via the XML editor <ref
                     target="https://www.oxygenxml.com/">Oxygen</ref>. Information pertaining to
                  named entities is integrated and cross-linked via a custom <ref
                     target="https://baserow.io/">Baserow</ref> database. </p>
               <p>In a first step, names, works, and places were marked up as entities, each of
                  which can be color-coded in the online edition via the “Annotations” menu. In the
                  index—where <ref target="listperson.html?lang=en">persons</ref> (historical as
                  well as fictional) and <ref target="listbibl.html?lang=en">works</ref> are further
                  linked with each other—and the detailed information of annotations, we used the
                  spelling of the <ref target="https://lobid.org/gnd">GND</ref> data base for person
                  names (if available in each case) and that of <ref
                     target="https://www.geonames.org/">GeoNames</ref> for place names. In the case
                  of names and places, only names and places themselves and terms directly related
                  to them are marked, not groups of people that have such references. For example,
                  “Griechenland” (“Greece”) and “griechisch” (“Greek”) are annotated, “Griechen”
                  (“Greeks”), however, are not, which then also applies to “Gluck” and “Piccini”, as
                  opposed to “Gluckisten” (“Gluckists”) and “Piccinisten” (“Piccinists”) (2.43).
                  Such terms can of course be found via a <ref target="search-engl.html?lang=en"
                     >full-text search</ref>.</p>
               <p>The guidelines for markup and textual layout mirror those of the treatise except
                  for three issues: (1) (2) Ambiguous indications of works—as in the case of, for
                  example, Schubert’s “A-Moll-Sonate” (Sonata in A minor), which Hanslick mentions
                  on December 1, 1864, without further clarification of which piano sonata he is
                  currently speaking (D537, D784, or D845)—are indicated by including multiple
                  references to the options in question. (3) On occasion, named entities might
                  include more than one title: (a) a main title, which in the case of an actual
                  person corresponds to the standard GND spelling and in the case of fictional
                  characters, works, and places matches the spelling of their respective native
                  language (rendered in Latin letters); (b) an alternative title reflecting the
                  spelling(s) and name(s) utilized by Hanslick. This way, users can successfully
                  search the index for, for example, Niccolò Piccinni, whom Hanslick at times spells
                  “Picinni” and “Piccini,” or Offenbachs <hi rend="italic">Les Géorgiennes</hi>,
                  which he names “Die Georgierinnern,” “Die schönen Georgierinnen,” and “Die schönen
                  Weiber von Georgien,” respectively.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
