<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hanslick Online – Index</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName resp="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1226158307">Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bäckerstraße 13</addrLine>
               <addrLine>1010 Vienna</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2023">2024</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body xml:lang="en-US">
         <div>
            <p>The website “Hanslick Online” provides the writings of Eduard Hanslick (1825–1904), a
               central figure of nineteenth-century music, who acted as an aesthetic theorist, music
               critic, and the first professor for the “History and Aesthetics of Musical Art” in
               German-language academia. It presents findings of several third-party-funded
               projects, in which <ref
                  target="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7568-3737">Christoph Landerer</ref> and <ref target="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0117-3574">Alexander Wilfing</ref> have been exploring the
               historical contexts of Hanslick and his works since 2014.</p>
            <p>Particular attention is paid to the numerous adaptations these texts have gone
               through during Hanslick’s lifetime. Besides making these texts (so far, 1. <ref
                  target="t__01_VMS_1854_TEI_AW_26-01-21-TEI-P5.html?lang=en"><emph>Vom
                     Musikalisch-Schönen</emph></ref>, 2. Hanslick’s writings for the <ref
                  target="toc.html"><emph>Neue Freie Presse</emph></ref>, and 3. reviews of the
               initial edition of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>) publicly available,
               “Hanslick Online” also facilitates automated comparisons between textual variants.
               The website thereby fills a gap in Hanslick scholarship, which is currently focusing
               more and more on the dynamic evolution and fluctuation of Hanslick’s mindset.</p>
            <p>The “Project” drop-down menu provides a brief sketch of <ref
                  target="bedeutung-hanslick-engl.html?lang=en">Hanslick’s historical
                  relevance</ref> from the nineteenth century to the present, explains the <ref
                  target="projektziele-engl.html?lang=en">intention and purpose</ref> of the present
               website, and recounts the <ref target="projektgeschichte-engl.html?lang=en">sequence
                  of research projects</ref>, the results of which led to the preparation of
               “Hanslick Online.” The scholarly outcome of these research projects may be viewed
               under the “Activities” subheading (<ref target="publikationen-engl.html?lang=en"
                  >publications</ref>, <ref target="einzelvortraege-engl.html?lang=en"
                  >presentations</ref>, and <ref target="veranstaltungen-engl.html?lang=en"
                  >events</ref>).</p>
            <p>Under the “Edition” drop-down menu, you will find the <ref
                  target="t__01_VMS_1854_TEI_AW_26-01-21-TEI-P5.html?lang=en">ten editions of
                     <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph></ref> and the option to compare variants
               by means of automated collation. By the end of 2025, Hanslick’s writings for the <ref
                  target="toc.html"><emph>Neue Freie Presse</emph></ref> and the reviews of
                  <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> will also be published, including TEI markup
               (in progress). As the culmination of the project series, a closing project has been
               granted in late 2024 that will fund both a commentary of <emph>Vom
                  Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> and the visualization of various textual
               properties.</p>
            <p>“Hanslick Online” is a work in progress, which we intend to expand in terms of
               content and digital functions in the not too distant future. If you have any ideas or
               suggestions for optimizing the digital edition and the website, or questions
               regarding Hanslick, the projects, and their scholarly outcome, please contact us via
               the contact details provided under “<ref target="team-engl.html?lang=en">Team</ref>.”
               Advice on errors or gaps in our data sets are especially welcome!</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
