<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hanslick Online - History of “Hanslick in Context”</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName resp="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1226158307">Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bäckerstraße 13</addrLine>
               <addrLine>1010 Vienna</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2023">2024</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body xml:lang="en-US">
         <div type="main">
            <head>History of “Hanslick in Context”</head>
            <byline>Alexander Wilfing, 2024</byline>
            <div type="inline">
               <p>“Hanslick in Context” is a long-term research project, conducted by <ref
                     target="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7568-3737">Christoph Landerer</ref> and
                     <ref target="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0117-3574">Alexander Wilfing</ref>
                  since 2014 as part of several individual projects located at the <ref
                     target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/en/">Austrian Academy of Sciences</ref>,
                  initially hosted by the <ref
                     target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/de/acdh/forschung/musikwissenschaft/geschichte-der-vorgaengerinstitutionen"
                     >Institute of History of Art and Musicology</ref> (2014–2019) and, as of 2020,
                  by the <ref target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/research/musicology">Austrian Centre
                     for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage, Department of Musicology</ref>
                  (ACDH-CD). Our research focuses on Hanslick’s historically significant treatise
                     <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen: Ein Beitrag zur Revision der Aesthetik der
                     Tonkunst</emph> (Leipzig: Rudolph Weigel, 1854; <emph>On the Musically
                     Beautiful: A Contribution to the Revision of the Aesthetics of
                  Music</emph>)—which during Hanslick’s lifetime appeared in ten revised editions—
                  Hanslick’s activities as a music critic, and his professorship in the “History and
                  Aesthetics of Musical Art” in Vienna, the earliest such position in
                  German-language academia. Landerer has examined Hanslick’s aesthetics repeatedly
                  since about 1990: his first study on the topic, “Bernard Bolzano, Eduard Hanslick
                  und die Geschichte des musikästhetischen Objektivismus,” was already published in
                  1993 in <emph>Kriterion</emph> (<ref
                     target="https://www.degruyter.com/journal/key/krt/5/1/html">no. 5</ref> and
                     <ref target="https://www.degruyter.com/journal/key/krt/6/1/html">no. 6</ref>),
                  and in 2001–2003 he visited the University of Toronto on an Erwin Schrödinger
                  Fellowship (<ref
                     target="https://www.fwf.ac.at/en/research-radar/10.55776/J1995"
                     >J1995</ref> / <ref
                        target="https://www.fwf.ac.at/en/research-radar/10.55776/J2161"
                        >J2161</ref>), conducting the research project “Eduard Hanslick’s
                  Musical Aesthetics in the Context of Austrian Intellectual History” with Geoffrey
                  Payzant, who had translated <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> into English in
                  1986 as <emph>On the Musically Beautiful</emph>. Wilfing’s research has dealt with
                  Hanslick since his dissertation <ref
                     target="https://utheses.univie.ac.at/detail/37993#"><emph>Eduard Hanslicks
                        Rezeption im englischen Sprachraum</emph></ref> (completed in 2016 and
                  published in 2019 as <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctvktrwbs"
                        ><emph>Re-Reading Hanslick’s Aesthetics</emph></ref>), which explores his
                  aesthetics as well as his impact on various disciplinary discourses, ranging from
                  musicology and music philosophy to music psychology, literary theory, art history,
                  and musical criticism. Moreover, he directed the project <ref
                     target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/research/musicology/research/project-archive/hanslick-adler-and-musicology"
                     >Creating an Academic Discipline: Eduard Hanslick, Guido Adler, and the
                     Establishment of Musicological Methodology in 19th-Century Vienna</ref> (Erwin
                  Schrödinger Fellowship <ref
                     target="https://www.fwf.ac.at/en/research-radar/10.55776/J4529"
                     >J4529</ref>) from 2021 to 2023—conducted at the <ref
                     target="https://www.aesthetics.mpg.de/en/research/department-of-music.html">Max
                     Planck Institute for Empirical Aesthetics</ref> (Frankfurt a.M.), <ref
                     target="https://www.muni.cz/en/about-us/organizational-structure/faculty-of-arts/213600-deptof-art-history"
                     >Masarykova Univerzita</ref> (Brno), and the ACDH-CH—which (among other things)
                  investigated Hanslick’s professorship, and has recently been analyzing Hanslick’s
                  critical writings. “Hanslick in Context,” which explores the historical background
                  of Hanslick’s activities as an aesthetic theorist, music critic, and musicologist,
                  consists—as of 2024—of the following individual research projects, for which
                  Landerer and Wilfing have received support from various funding bodies: </p>
                  <figure>
                     <graphic url="images/Projektgeschichte_Hanslick_Kongress_new.jpg"></graphic>
                     <head>Program of the <ref
                        target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/de/acdh/detail/news/eduard-hanslick-im-kontext-3"
                        >conference “Hanslick im Kontext,”</ref> photograph by Franz Pflügl; by
                     courtesy of the University of Vienna</head>
                     <!--<figDesc>...</figDesc>-->
                  </figure>
               </div>
            <div type="block">
               <list type="bibl">
                  <item>2014–2017, <ref
                     target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/research/musicology/research/project-archive/hanslick-in-context"
                        >Hanslick in Context: Hanslick’s Aesthetic Ideas, Their Genesis, and Their
                        Place in the History of Ideas</ref> (stand-alone project, funded by the
                     Austrian Science Fund FWF, <ref
                        target="https://www.fwf.ac.at/en/research-radar/10.55776/P26610"
                        >P26610</ref>, P.I. Christoph Landerer)</item>
                  <item>2017–2018, <ref
                     target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/research/musicology/research/project-archive/hanslick-in-context"
                        >Studies in the Genesis of Hanslick’s <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>:
                        Textual and Contextual Analysis</ref> (stand-alone project, funded by the
                     Anniversary Fund of the Austrian Central Bank, 17508, P.I. Christoph
                     Landerer)</item>
                  <item>2018–2021, <ref
                     target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/research/musicology/research/project-archive/hanslick-in-context"
                        >Eduard Hanslick’s <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>: An Analysis of the
                        Dynamic Features of the Text and Its Contexts</ref> (stand-alone project,
                     funded by the Austrian Science Fund FWF, <ref
                        target="https://www.fwf.ac.at/en/research-radar/10.55776/P30554"
                        >P30554</ref>, P.I. Christoph Landerer)</item>
                  <item>2022–2025, <ref
                     target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/research/musicology/research/composers-editions/hanslicks-criticism"
                        >Eduard Hanslick’s Criticism Between Aesthetics, Journalism, and
                        Scholarship</ref> (stand-alone project, funded by the Austrian Science Fund
                     FWF, <ref
                        target="https://www.fwf.ac.at/en/research-radar/10.55776/P35379"
                        >P35379</ref>, P.I. Alexander Wilfing)</item>
                  <item>2024–2025, <ref
                        target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/research/musicology/research/composers-editions/criticizing-hanslick"
                        >The Critic Under Scrutiny: The Reviews of Eduard Hanslick’s On the
                        Musically Beautiful (1854–1857)</ref> (stand-alone project, funded by the
                     City of Vienna, P.I. Alexander Wilfing)</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="inline">
               <figure>
                  <graphic url="images/Projektgeschichte_Collage_Kontext_new.jpg"></graphic>
                  <head>Collage of images of <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernard_Bolzano#/media/Datei:Bernard_Bolzano_Kriehuber.jpg">Bolzano</ref>, <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georg_Wilhelm_Friedrich_Hegel#/media/Datei:1831_Schlesinger_Philosoph_Georg_Friedrich_Wilhelm_Hegel_anagoria.JPG">Hegel</ref>, <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Friedrich_Herbart#/media/Datei:Johann_F_Herbart.jpg">Herbart</ref>, and <ref target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kritik_der_Urteilskraft#/media/Datei:Immanuel_Kant_(painted_portrait).jpg">Kant</ref> (Wikipedia Creative Commons)</head>
               </figure>
               <p>“Hanslick in Context,” presenting the foundation for ensuing research ventures,
                  aimed at critically analyzing the “eclectic” intellectual background of Hanslick’s
                  aesthetics, the genetic factors of which were made transparent from an overarching
                  perspective. Here, we focused on grasping Hanslick’s method of selectively
                  integrating different philosophical discourses as well as his use of textual
                  sources, thereby providing a stable basis for Hanslick scholarship, which has
                  reached strikingly disparate findings in assessing the historical background of
                     <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>. In a first step, we took into account
                  various positions in nineteenth-century aesthetic discourse, whose respective
                  relevance for Hanslick’s reasoning had for the most part been scrutinized
                  separately. In consideration of our hypothesis that Hanslick’s treatise cannot be
                  assigned to any individual philosophical movement and that it is of a quasi-hybrid
                  nature, we analyzed the various sources of his remarks and methods in a broad
                  fashion. In addition to philosophers prominent in Hanslick literature—e.g.
                  Bolzano, Hegel, Herbart, Kant, Vischer, and Zimmermann—we integrated lesser-known
                  figures such as Gutt, Hand, Michaelis, Nägeli, and Weisse into this discursive
                  formation. We moreover examined the parameters of Habsburg education policy and
                  its influence on Hanslick’s aesthetics, which evolved in intimate contact with the
                  Austrian Ministry of Education—led by Count von Thun und Hohenstein—the
                  empirical-formalistic orientation of which also shaped some of his primary
                  doctrines. In addition to Hanslick’s contacts with central figures of the Thun
                  reform, we analyzed the genetic aspects of his aesthetic position. Besides
                  content-related factors, this included questions concerning methodology, e.g.
                  Hanslick’s juridical training and the scientific-theoretical orientation of
                  Austria. In this vein, we were able to integrate established
                  intellectual-historical research methods with current trends towards a broader
                  historical contextualization of Hanslick’s <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>,
                  consequently demonstrating how the genetic context of this book illuminates the
                  intellectual foundations of Hanslick’s aesthetics. We thus made clear how the
                  complex and neglected interplay between philosophical orientations, specific
                  aesthetic traditions, institutional and political settings, and personal relations
                  affected Hanslick’s positions, which did not mature in post-1848 Vienna by
                  historical accident. It is only against this diversified background that one can
                  hope to grasp the peculiarities of an aesthetic approach which otherwise defies
                  proper classification in terms of intellectual coordinates and was devised in a
                  wide field of tension between philosophical, aesthetic, political, scientific, and
                  juridical discourses.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="inline">
               <p>The project “Studies in the Genesis of Hanslick’s <emph>Vom
                     Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>” continued this work along these lines and expanded
                  our research approach by including the dimension of the historical evolution of
                  the book itself, which was now investigated from a more systematic perspective.
                     <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> was now considered a dynamic textual
                  corpus, which permits claims regarding “the” aesthetics of Eduard Hanslick solely
                  on basis of detailed genetic studies. The genetic and historical dimension of the
                  text was analyzed carefully as regards the emergence of this book from
                  pre-publications of 1853 and 1854 (chapters 4, 5, and 6), the chronological as
                  well as logical order of the seven chapters, and the crucial changes in the new
                  editions of 1858 (2nd edition) and 1865 (3rd edition), which are also important
                  regarding Hanslick’s reception in aesthetic discourse. <emph>Vom
                     Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> thus appears neither as an “aphoristic” collection
                  of older texts, nor as a purposefully straightforward monograph, but as a text
                  with a complex argumentative structure, which can only be grasped by means of
                  specific genetic analyses. Our reconstruction of the chronological and logical
                  fabric of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> revealed a surprising chapter
                  sequence (6, 4, 5, 1, 2, 3, 7) that contradicts the familiar sequence of published
                  chapters. We combined this textual problem with the continued examination of
                  relevant contexts, which might have caused the corresponding textual changes and
                  ongoing variation of Hanslick’s arguments in a direct manner. Here, we also
                  focused on Hanslick’s political contexts and institutional affiliations, which
                  proved crucial for the realization of his academic career strategy. Apart from
                  these contextual and textual studies, we moreover included empirical documents
                  (letters, files, etc.), which provided an additional methodological dimension and
                  added depth to our research findings. These (unfortunately rather sparse)
                  documents were furthermore supplemented by a detailed analysis of Hanslick’s
                  personal contacts with prominent nineteenth-century aesthetic theorists (e.g.
                  Robert Zimmermann) and the overall political situation in Vienna; on that front,
                  we considered Hanslick’s activities at Count Thun’s Ministry of Education and its
                  positivistic orientation to be of particular relevance. Such contexts also
                  illuminated significant modifications in edition 2 of <emph>Vom
                     Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>, which retracts remnants of Romantic aesthetics and
                  reinforces its formalistic orientation.</p>
               <figure>
                  <graphic url="images/Projektgeschichte_Hanslick_Vorabdruck_new.jpg"></graphic>
                  <head>The eventual chapter no. 6, <ref
                        target="https://books.google.de/books?id=kMlLAAAAcAAJ&amp;hl=de&amp;pg=PA78#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                        >“Die Tonkunst in ihren Beziehungen zur Natur”</ref></head>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="inline">
               <figure>
                  <graphic url="images/Projektgeschichte_Hanslick_Auflagen_new.jpg"></graphic>
                  <head><emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>, <ref
                        target="https://archive.org/details/VomMusikalischSchnen1tea1854/mode/2up"
                        >edition 1 (1854)</ref> and <ref
                        target="https://archive.org/details/VomMusikalischSchnen10tea1902/mode/2up"
                        >edition 10 (1902)</ref></head>
               </figure>
               <p>The project “Eduard Hanslick’s <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>: An Analysis
                  of the Dynamic Features of the Text and Its Contexts” resumed our treatment of
                  Hanslick’s aesthetic treatise as a <emph>dynamic</emph> corpus of textual
                  material, while significantly expanding our respective investigation. The period
                  of analysis now covered the years 1848 to 1902 and thereby included all ten
                  versions of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> that were edited by Hanslick
                  during his lifetime, as well as the evolution of his arguments in preliminary
                  publications and remarks on the themes of his aesthetic treatise in his musical
                  criticism and other textual formats. This substantial expansion of the time frame
                  of our investigation also corresponded to a newly developed and much more
                  comprehensive understanding of the central contexts. We now proceeded to
                  distinguish between the <emph>theoretical</emph> contexts of <emph>Vom
                     Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> and its stages of continuous development (essential
                  theoretical discourses in a broad sense with the core areas of philosophy,
                  science, music theory) and the <emph>practical</emph> contexts of this book
                  (political setting, institutional affiliations, personal networks). Said
                  theoretical contextual fields were examined in great detail both at the
                     <emph>intra</emph>discursive level (development of the individual discursive
                  formations) and the <emph>inter</emph>discursive level (interaction of the
                  discursive formations with each other). The specific analyses covered three areas:
                  (a) the historical evolution of Hanslick’s arguments from approx. 1848 to the
                  initial edition of 1854, (b) the genesis, layout, and structure of the arguments
                  within the wording of edition 1 and primarily the conceptual development of
                  central notions within the chapters, and (c) Hanslick’s variation of essential
                  arguments in later editions, up to edition 10 of 1902. This approach was moreover
                  intended to replace a rather static understanding of Hanslick’s aesthetics with a
                  dynamic reading, capable of illuminating how elementary references, ideas, and
                  terms are transformed continuously from the individual perspective of Hanslick’s
                  various editions. This very “dynamization” of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>
                  contributed significantly to a fuller grasp and more appropriate understanding of
                  this essential aesthetic treatise, the historical reception of which frequently
                  overlooks how the dynamic properties of contexts and text(s) deeply affect our
                  interpretation of Hanslick’s concepts and methods.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="inline">
               <p>The project “Eduard Hanslick’s Criticism Between Aesthetics, Journalism, and
                  Scholarship” now shifts the focus of our ongoing research to Hanslick’s critical
                  writings, while retaining our attention to questions of textual analysis. While
                  scholarship has so far focused chiefly on analyzing and interpreting Hanslick’s
                  aesthetics and situating his theoretical reasoning in the context of his age, the
                  current project explores the relation between the various textual genres of his
                  oeuvre, which remains unclear to this very day. For if in <emph>Vom
                     Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>, for example, Hanslick casts doubt on the frequently
                  postulated correlation between emotion and music from an aesthetic perspective,
                  his critical articles are interspersed with expressive metaphors that at first
                  glance conflict with the maxims of his treatise. Other supposed deviations most
                  likely result from the fact that Hanslick’s activities as a music critic spanned
                  some sixty years (1844–1904) and developed dynamically over time, while his
                  aesthetic treatise—which he usually altered only slightly in later revised
                  editions—remained relatively static. The project thus explores the dynamics of
                  these fluid processes and analyzes to what extent Hanslick’s critical writings are
                  compatible with <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>, whether genuine
                  contradictions arise, or whether later texts can even be read as an elaboration of
                  his aesthetic approach, which has failed to sufficiently theorize essential
                  questions such as the performative nature of music. Here, the project will
                  furthermore reconstruct Hanslick’s criteria for selecting and editing certain
                  essays for the (sometimes thoroughly modified) textual versions provided in his
                  various anthologies, thereby seeking clarification about shifts in Hanslick’s
                  positions. Moreover, as he conceived of these collected volumes as a “living
                  history” of music in Vienna, they will be cross-read with Hanslick’s conception of
                  academic musical research. This view will then be extended to Hanslick’s concrete
                  language use (expression, speech figures, metaphors, etc.), opening the project to
                  an analysis of cultural, political, and general historical contexts as well as
                  their shifts over time, which will become the focal point of a follow-up project.
                  The textual analysis is based on the digital edition of <emph>Vom
                     Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> (2023) and the transcription / TEI annotation of
                  Hanslick’s writings for the <emph>Neue Freie Presse</emph> (1864–1904) and his 12
                  anthologies, which are being put online in an ongoing process.</p>
               <figure>
                  <graphic url="images/Projektgeschichte_Hanslick_Karikatur.jpg"></graphic>
                  <head>Eduard Hanslick and Richard Wagner, silhouette by Otto Böhler; by courtesy
                     of <ref target="https://onb.digital/result/10F2ECCA">Österreichische
                        Nationalbibliothek</ref></head>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="inline">
               <figure>
                  <graphic url="images/Projektgeschichte_VMS_Kritiken.jpg"></graphic>
                  <head>Franz Brendel, review of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>, <ref
                        target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb10527933?page=93"
                           ><emph>Neue Zeitschrift für Musik</emph>, February 16, 1855</ref></head>
               </figure>
               <p>The project „The Critic under Scrutiny: The Reviews of Eduard Hanslick’s <emph>Vom
                     Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> (1854–1857)“ takes a closer look at the development
                  of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> by examining reviews of the initial
                  edition as a catalyst for changes in Hanslick’s argument. Alongside the more
                  widely known reviews by Robert Zimmermann and Hermann Lotze, 26 reviews appeared
                  between the end of 1854 and the end of 1857, when the second edition of Hanslick’s
                  treatise was published. Pertinent examples include a four-part review by Ludwig
                  Bischoff (<emph>Niederrheinische Musik-Zeitung</emph>, <ref
                     target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/en/view/bsb10527506?page=59"
                     >February 17</ref>, <ref
                     target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/en/view/bsb10527506?page=67"
                     >February 24</ref>, <ref
                     target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/en/view/bsb10527506?page=75">March
                     3</ref>, and <ref
                     target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/en/view/bsb10527506?page=83">March
                     10, 1855</ref>), a three-part review by Franz Brendel (<emph>Neue Zeitschrift
                     für Musik</emph>, <ref
                     target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb10527933?page=93"
                     >February 16</ref>, <ref
                     target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb10527933?page=105"
                     >February 23</ref>, and <ref
                     target="https://www.digitale-sammlungen.de/de/view/bsb10527933?page=113">March
                     2, 1855</ref>), as well as a review in <emph>Dwight’s Journal of Music</emph>
                     (<ref
                     target="https://archive.org/details/dwightsjournalm03dwiggoog/page/n130/mode/1up?view=theater"
                     >July 21, 1855</ref>). The project team will process these reviews as annotated
                  XML/TEI files and make them available as a distinct textual corpus. Beyond this
                  edition, we will also analyze the extent to which Hanslick explicitly addressed or
                  implicitly responded to criticism, and whether he borrowed passages from these
                  reviews in ensuing editions. This project on the earliest reviews of <emph>Vom
                     Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> thus not only enriches our understanding of
                  Hanslick’s reception and the aesthetic and musical debates of the nineteenth
                  century; it moreover contributes to the reconstruction of the emergence and
                  development of a text that remains central to music philosophy today.</p>
               
            </div>
            <div type="block">
               <p>The majority of projects were supported by numerous “international collaborators,”
                  for whose assistance and dedicated cooperation we thoroughly appreciate. These
                  collaborations included the following partnerships: </p>
               <list>
                  <item>Hanslick in Context: Hanslick’s Aesthetic Ideas, Their Genesis, and Their
                     Place in the History of Ideas: <ref
                        target="https://music.unc.edu/people/musicfaculty/mark-evan-bonds/">Mark
                        Evan Bonds</ref> (University of North Carolina at Chapell Hill), <ref
                           target="https://profiles.auckland.ac.nz/sj-davies">Stephen Davies</ref>
                     (University of Auckland), <ref
                        target="https://philosophy.columbia.edu/content/lydia-goehr">Lydia
                        Goehr</ref> (Columbia University in the City of New York), <ref
                           target="https://profiles.stanford.edu/thomas-grey">Thomas S. Grey</ref>
                     (Stanford University), <ref target="https://nicolegrimes.org/">Nicole
                        Grimes</ref> (University College Dublin), <ref
                           target="https://music.ucsb.edu/people/emeriti/lee-rothfarb">Lee
                           Rothfarb</ref> (University of California, Santa Barbara), and <ref
                              target="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/philosophy/prof-nick-zangwill">Nick
                              Zangwill</ref> (University College London).</item>
                  <item>Studies in the Genesis of Hanslick’s <emph>Vom
                     Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>: Textual and Contextual Analysis: <ref
                        target="https://music.unc.edu/people/musicfaculty/mark-evan-bonds/">Mark
                        Evan Bonds</ref> (University of North Carolina at Chapell Hill), <ref
                           target="https://music.ucsb.edu/people/emeriti/lee-rothfarb">Lee
                           Rothfarb</ref> (University of California, Santa Barbara), and <ref
                              target="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/philosophy/prof-nick-zangwill">Nick
                              Zangwill</ref> (University College London).</item>
                  <item>Eduard Hanslick’s <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>: An Analysis of
                     the Dynamic Features of the Text and Its Contexts: <ref
                        target="https://music.unc.edu/people/musicfaculty/mark-evan-bonds/">Mark
                        Evan Bonds</ref> (University of North Carolina at Chapell Hill), <ref
                           target="https://www.music.ox.ac.uk/people/dr-bojan-bujic">Bojan
                           Bujic</ref> (University of Oxford), <ref
                              target="https://profiles.stanford.edu/thomas-grey">Thomas S. Grey</ref>
                     (Stanford University), <ref
                        target="https://www.musik.uzh.ch/de/mitarbeiter/emeriti/hinrichsen/hinrichsen-cv.html/"
                        >Hans-Joachim Hinrichsen</ref> (University of Zurich), <ref
                           target="https://music.ucsb.edu/people/emeriti/lee-rothfarb">Lee
                           Rothfarb</ref> (University of California, Santa Barbara), Dietmar Strauß
                     (Schwalbach, Germany), and <ref
                        target="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/philosophy/prof-nick-zangwill">Nick
                        Zangwill</ref> (University College London).</item>
                  <item>Eduard Hanslick’s Criticism Between Aesthetics, Journalism, and
                     Scholarship: <ref target="https://profiles.stanford.edu/thomas-grey">Thomas
                        S. Grey</ref> (Stanford University), <ref target="https://ninanoeske.de/"
                           >Nina Noeske</ref> (Hochschule für Musik und Theater Hamburg / Hochschule
                     für Musik Franz Liszt Weimar), <ref
                        target="https://goldsmiths.academia.edu/AnthonyPryer">Anthony Pryer</ref>
                     (Goldsmiths, University of London), <ref
                        target="https://music.ucsb.edu/people/emeriti/lee-rothfarb">Lee
                        Rothfarb</ref> (University of California, Santa Barbara), and <ref
                           target="https://music.uchicago.edu/people/lawrence-zbikowski">Lawrence
                           Zbikowski</ref> (University of Chicago).</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
