<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hanslick Online - Project Targets of “Hanslick Online”</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName resp="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1226158307">Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bäckerstraße 13</addrLine>
               <addrLine>1010 Vienna</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2023">2024</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body xml:lang="en-US">
         <div type="main">
            <head>Project Targets of “Hanslick Online”</head>
            <byline>Alexander Wilfing, 2024</byline>
            <div type="block">
               <p>The website “Hanslick Online,” which emerged directly from the long-term research
                  project “<ref target="projektgeschichte-engl.html">Hanslick in Context</ref>,”
                  enables comparisons between different items of Eduard Hanslick’s writings: on the
                  one hand between the ten editions of his central treatise <ref
                     target="VMS_Auflage_01_1854.xml.html?lang=en"><emph>Vom
                        Musikalisch-Schönen</emph></ref> edited during his lifetime, on the other
                  hand between his writings for the <emph>Neue Freie Presse</emph> and the 12
                  anthologies he constructed from these texts (this feature is currently being
                  developed), which may be found in <ref target="bedeutung-hanslick-engl.html">this
                     list</ref> (see “Eduard Hanslick’s Writings”). In the not too distant future,
                  “Hanslick Online” will also provide an automated collation between the treatise,
                  the reviews, and the anthologies, the preparation of which will have to be funded
                  within the framework of a further research project aligned with the needs of this
                  specific textual corpus. “Hanslick Online” thereby responds to several concrete
                  problems of Hanslick research and thus also sets a number of goals: </p>
               <div type="block">
                  <list type="bibl">
                     <item>Since Hanslick’s estate was lost during the Second World War, no
                        manuscripts, drafts, or sketches of his works are known (until today). The
                        prints we edited and present here thus make up the primary sources for
                        Hanslick research. They are now accessible to each user as a digital edition
                        with TEI markup and full-text search and should establish themselves as a
                        standard resource for Hanslick studies and beyond.</item>
                     <item>Apart from Dietmar Strauß’s historical-critical edition of Hanslick’s
                        writings, which he managed to continue until reaching the year 1865
                        (1993–2001), his reviews have chiefly remained familiar as part of his own
                        and other people’s collected volumes. With its nearly 900 original reviews,
                        “Hanslick Online” thereby provides an improved overview of the broader
                        spectrum of Hanslick’s activity as a music critic.</item>
                     <item>Hanslick revised <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> many a time for
                        biographical, political, and content-related reasons. “Hanslick Online”
                        marks these changes visually and facilitates comparisons of paragraphs from
                        individual or all ten editions, making it easier to reconstruct the
                        development of this book and to systematically contextualize the various
                        revisions.</item>
                     <item>In addition to editing and analyzing texts provided by Hanslick himself,
                        we are including reviews of his aesthetic treatise to assess whether, and to
                        what extent, he responded to critiques of the initial edition of <hi
                           rend="italic">Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</hi> through revisions in the
                        second edition. Furthermore, it will soon be possible to create links
                        between different editions (such as the editions of <hi rend="italic">On the
                           Musically Beautiful</hi> and its reviews).</item>
                     <item>Previous Hanslick research has frequently attempted to get to
                           <emph>the</emph> heart of Hanslick’s aesthetic conception, and in doing
                        so often blurred the tension between specific editions. “Hanslick in
                        Context,” in contrast, reflects the <emph>dynamics</emph> of Hanslick’s
                        position(s), the variation and evolution of which becomes truly tangible for
                        the first time by means of “Hanslick Online.”</item>
                     <item>Comparisons between his aesthetic treatise and later texts is also of
                        importance for the dynamics of Hanslick’s positions. The full-text search
                        allows for a largely complete overview of cardinal concepts as well as their
                        function and purpose in Hanslick’s views on music, which are to be
                        scrutinized for coherences, differences, alterations, and developments
                        beyond <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>.</item>
                     <item>Hanslick more than once used his own textual material on several
                        different occasions: for example, he adopted passages from earlier reviews
                        in <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> and incorporated textual material
                        from other books and articles in ensuing editions. As Hanslick only very
                        rarely reveals such passages as quotations, “Hanslick Online” will help in
                        detecting hitherto uncharted transfers between writings.</item>
                     <item>This point applies above all to his anthologies, which Hanslick compiled
                        from reviews, reports, and essays that had already been printed. On
                        occasion, Hanslick even merged several reviews of the same piece into a book
                        chapter or moved and included specific passages of an essay he did not
                        integrate. In these cases, which can hardly be detected manually, a
                        mechanical text comparison will ease respective research endeavors.</item>
                     <item>For Hanslick, moreover, his anthologies presented scholarly publications,
                        an “aesthetic statistics” of the Viennese music scene of his era. An
                        investigation of the criteria by which he chose to select and revise certain
                        articles for the anthologies at the expense of others using the collation
                        features provided by “Hanslick Online” will thus also provide insights into
                        Hanslick's concept of musical aesthetics and historiography.</item>
                     <item>Finally, any reading of Hanslick’s aesthetics is at least indirectly
                        determined by the specific edition of <emph>Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</emph>
                        used in each case. German-language Hanslick research, which often situates
                        him in the tradition of idealistic aesthetics, usually takes edition 1 as
                        its hermeneutic foundation. By comparison, editions 7, 9, and 10—from which
                        Hanslick removed some idealist passages—are available in English rendition,
                        which feeds into a more formalist reading. This, as Geoffrey Payzant
                        observes astutely, also leads to fundamental differences in German-language
                        and English-language Hanslick research: “When we compare the secondary
                        literature in English about Eduard Hanslick’s <emph>Vom
                           Musikalisch-Schönen</emph> with that in German we get the impression that
                        commentators in German are writing about one book and commentators in
                        English about quite another” (<emph>Hanslick on the Musically Beautiful:
                           Sixteen Lectures on the Musical Aesthetics of Eduard Hanslick</emph>,
                        Christchurch: Cybereditions, 2002, 44.) An exhaustive comparison of editions
                        thus reveals not only the genesis of this book itself but also the formation
                        of surrounding discourses and patterns of reception, which are to be
                        explored as part of future research projects.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
