<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hanslick Online - Events</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName resp="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1226158307">Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bäckerstraße 13</addrLine>
               <addrLine>1010 Vienna</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2023">2025</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body xml:lang="en-US">
         <div type="main">
            <head>Events</head>
            <byline>April 07, 2025</byline>
            <div type="block">
               <list type="bibl">
                  <item>2025/09. “<ref
                        target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/research/musicology/research/composers-editions/hanslicks-criticism/eduard-hanslick-1825-2025"
                        >Eduard Hanslick, 1825–2025: Background, Context, Legacy</ref>,” bilingual
                     international symposium on occasion of Eduard Hanslick’s 200th birthday,
                     organized by Alexander Wilfing, Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and
                     Cultural Heritage, Austrian Academy of Sciences, funded in-house by the
                     ACDH-CH.</item>
                  <item>2025/05. “The Aesthetic Legacy of Eduard Hanslick,” book launch event of <hi
                        rend="italic">The Aesthetic Legacy of Eduard Hanslick: Close Readings and
                        Critical Perspectives</hi> (New York: Routledge, 2025), organized by
                     Alexander Wilfing; speakers: Thomas S. Grey, Christoph Landerer, and Nick
                     Zangwill; Online Connections Seminar, European Network for the Philosophy of
                     Music.</item>
                  <item>2025/03. “<ref
                        target="https://www.daad.cam.ac.uk/workshops/composer-critics-and-their-music-reflections-on-minds-of-the-nineteenth-century#overview"
                        >Composer-Critics and Their Music: Reflections on Minds of the Nineteenth
                        Century</ref>,” workshop organized by Alexander Wilfing in collaboration
                     with David Trippett, Christ’s College, Cambridge, funded by the DAAD.</item>
                  <item>2024/07. “<ref
                        target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/news/auch-klassische-komponisten-hatten-beefs"
                        >Auch klassische Komponisten hatten Beefs</ref>,” interview with Alexander
                     Wilfing for the Austrian Academy of Sciences, moderated by Karin Cerny.</item>
                  <item>2024/05. „<ref
                     target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zIbSLcYHQSg"
                     >Der Kritiker als Komponist: Eduard Hanslicks Liedschaffen / The
                     Critic as Composer: The Songs of Eduard Hanslick</ref>“, recording of the lecture
                     recital of September 2023; concept and organization: Alexander Wilfing
                     (Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage, Austrian Academy
                     of Sciences) and Anja Bunzel (Institute of Art History, Czech Academy of
                     Sciences); Camera: Bernhard Graf (Phonogrammarchiv, Austrian Academy of
                     Sciences) and Johannes Spitzbart (Phonogrammarchiv, Austrian Academy of
                     Sciences); Editing: Johannes Spitzbart; <ref
                        target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/fileadmin/Institute/ACDH/img/News_Events/Song_Texts.pdf"
                        >song texts</ref><ref type="video"
                        target="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zIbSLcYHQSg"/>.</item>
                  <item>2024/01. “<ref
                        target="https://sonograma.org/2024/01/alexander-wilfing-walking-in-the-steps-of-eduard-hanslick/"
                        >Alexander Wilfing: Walking in the Steps of Eduard Hanslick</ref>,”
                     interview with Alexander Wilfing for the magazine <hi rend="italic"
                        >sonograma</hi>, moderated by Mercedes de Luis Andrés.</item>
                  <item>2023/09. “<ref
                        target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/detail/event/der-kritiker-als-komponist-eduard-hanslicks-liedschaffen"
                        >Der Kritiker als Komponist: Eduard Hanslicks Liedschaffen</ref>,” lecture
                     recital organized by Alexander Wilfing (Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities
                     and Cultural Heritage, Austrian Academy of Sciences) and Anja Bunzel (Institute
                     of Art History, Czech Academy of Sciences) at the Austrian Centre for Digital
                     Humanities and Cultural Heritage, Austrian Academy of Sciences. Concert program
                     available at <ref
                        target="https://www.academia.edu/106512915/Booklet_Hanslick_Concert_Vienna_September_29_2023_"
                        >https://www.academia.edu/106512915/Booklet_Hanslick_Concert_Vienna_September_29_2023_</ref>.</item>
                  <item>2023/04. “Geschichte, Gegenwart und Zukunft der Musikwissenschaft(en),”
                     workshop at the Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage,
                     organized by Alexander Wilfing, Austrian Academy of Sciences, funded by the
                     Austrian Science Fund FWF.</item>
                  <item>2020/04. “New Directions in Hanslick Scholarship,” workshop organized by
                     Christoph Landerer and Alexander Wilfing at the Department of Musicology,
                     University of Vienna, funded by the Austrian Science Fund FWF and the Austrian
                     Academy of Sciences (cancelled due to COVID-19 pandemic).</item>
                  <item>2019/07. Organisation of the special session “Hanslick’s Concepts: Meaning,
                     Translation, Reception,” 7th Biennial Music and Philosophy Conference, London;
                     organisation: Alexander Wilfing; presenters: Christoph Landerer, Lee Rothfarb,
                     and Alexander Wilfing; for further details and the program, see <ref
                        target="https://musicandphilosophy.ac.uk/events/mpsg-2019/"
                        >https://musicandphilosophy.ac.uk/events/mpsg-2019/</ref>.</item>
                  <item>2017/03. “Probleme der Hanslick-Forschung,” workshop at the Institute of
                     History of Art and Musicology, Austrian Academy of Sciences, organized by
                     Christoph Landerer and Alexander Wilfing, funded by the Austrian Academy of
                     Sciences and the City of Vienna.</item>
                  <item>2016/12. “<ref
                        target="https://oe1.orf.at/programm/20161205/453376/Apropos-Musik">Der böse
                        Besserwisser: Eduard Hanslick</ref>,” interview with Christoph Landerer, Lee
                     Rothfarb, and Alexander Wilfing for the radio program “Apropos Musik” (Ö1),
                     conducted by Johannes Leopold Mayer.</item>
                  <item>2016/09. “Hanslick im Kontext / Hanslick in Context,” bilingual
                     international conference, organized by Christoph Landerer and Alexander
                     Wilfing, Austrian Society for Music, funded by the Austrian Science Fund FWF,
                     the Austrian Academy of Sciences, and the City of Vienna; for further details
                     and the program, see <ref target="http://hanslick2016.com/"
                        >http://hanslick2016.com/</ref> and <ref
                        target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/de/acdh/detail/news/eduard-hanslick-im-kontext-3"
                        >https://www.oeaw.ac.at/de/acdh/detail/news/eduard-hanslick-im-kontext-3</ref>.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
