<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hanslick Online - Events</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <orgName resp="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1226158307">Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Bäckerstraße 13</addrLine>
               <addrLine>1010 Vienna</addrLine>
            </address>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2023">2023</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body xml:lang="en-US">
         <div type="main">
            <head>Events</head>
            <byline>April 16, 2024</byline>
            <div type="block">
               <list type="bibl">
                  <item>2024/01. “<ref
                        target="https://sonograma.org/2024/01/alexander-wilfing-walking-in-the-steps-of-eduard-hanslick/"
                        >Alexander Wilfing: Walking in the Steps of Eduard Hanslick</ref>,”
                     interview with Alexander Wilfing for the magazine <hi rend="italic"
                        >sonograma</hi>, moderated by Mercedes de Luis Andrés</item>
                  <item>2023/09. “<ref target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/detail/event/der-kritiker-als-komponist-eduard-hanslicks-liedschaffen">Der Kritiker als Komponist: Eduard Hanslicks Liedschaffen</ref>,”
                     lecture recital organized by Alexander Wilfing and Anja Bunzel (Institute of
                     Art History, Czech Academy of Sciences) at the Austrian Centre for Digital
                     Humanities and Cultural Heritage, Austrian Academy of Sciences.</item>
                  <item>2023/04. “Geschichte, Gegenwart und Zukunft der Musikwissenschaft(en),”
                     workshop at the Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage,
                     Austrian Academy of Sciences, funded by the Austrian Science Fund FWF.</item>
                  <item>2020/04. “New Directions in Hanslick Scholarship,” workshop at the
                     Department of Musicology, University of Vienna, funded by the Austrian Science
                     Fund FWF and the Austrian Academy of Sciences (cancelled due to COVID-19
                     pandemic).</item>
                  <item>2019/07. Organisation of the special session “Hanslick’s Concepts: Meaning,
                     Translation, Reception,” 7th Biennial Music and Philosophy Conference, London;
                     organisation: Alexander Wilfing; presenters: Christoph Landerer, Lee Rothfarb,
                     and Alexander Wilfing; for further details and the program, see <ref
                        target="https://musicandphilosophy.ac.uk/events/mpsg-2019/"
                        >https://musicandphilosophy.ac.uk/events/mpsg-2019/</ref>.</item>
                  <item>2017/03. “Probleme der Hanslick-Forschung,” workshop at the Institute of
                     History of Art and Musicology, Austrian Academy of Sciences, funded by the
                     Austrian Academy of Sciences and the City of Vienna.</item>
                  <item>2016/12. “<ref
                        target="https://oe1.orf.at/programm/20161205/453376/Apropos-Musik">Der böse
                        Besserwisser: Eduard Hanslick</ref>,” interview with Christoph Landerer, Lee
                     Rothfarb, and Alexander Wilfing for the radio program “Apropos Musik” (Ö1),
                     conducted by Johannes Leopold Mayer</item>
                  <item>2016/09. “Hanslick im Kontext / Hanslick in Context,” bilingual
                     international conference, Austrian Society for Music, funded by the Austrian
                     Science Fund FWF, the Austrian Academy of Sciences, and the City of Vienna; for
                     further details and the program, see <ref target="http://hanslick2016.com/"
                        >http://hanslick2016.com/</ref> and <ref
                           target="https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/musicology/detail/eduard-hanslick-im-kontext-3"
                           >https://www.oeaw.ac.at/acdh/musicology/detail/eduard-hanslick-im-kontext-3</ref>.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
